all right today I want to talk about bit
more about fault tolerance and
replication and then look into the
details of today's paper about vmware ft
the topics still fault tolerance to
provide high availability that is you
want to build a server that even if some
hardware you know computer crashes is
involved in the service we still like to
provide the service and to the extent we
can we'd like to provide our service
also if there's network problems and the
tool we're using its replication least
for this part of the course so it's
worth asking what kind of failures
replication can be expected to deal with
because it's not everything by any means
so maybe the easiest way to characterize
the kind of failures we're talking about
is fail stop failures of a single
computer and what I mean by fail stop
it's a sort of generic term and fault
tolerance is that if something goes
wrong would say the computer the
computer simply stops executing it just
stops if anything goes wrong and in
particular it doesn't compute incorrect
results so if somebody kicks the power
cable out of your server that's probably
gonna generate a fail stop failure
similarly if they unplug your servers
network connection even though the
server is still running so this is a
little bit funny you know be totally cut
off from the network so it looks at me
outside like it just stopped so it's
really these failures we can deal with
with replication this also covers some
hardware problems like you know maybe if
the fan on your server breaks because it
you know it cost 50 cents maybe that'll
cause the CPU to overheat and the CPU
will shut itself down cleanly and just
stop executing
what's not covered by the kind of
replication systems we're talking about
is things like bugs and software or
design defects in hardware so basically
not bugs because if we take some service
you know say you're a MapReduce master
for example you know we replicated and
run it on two computers you know if
there's a bug in your MapReduce master
or my MapReduce master let's say
replications not going to help us we're
going to compute the same incorrect
result on both of our copies of our
MapReduce master and everything looked
fine they'll agree you just happen to be
the wrong answer so we can't depending
against bugs in the replicated software
and we can't defend against bugs in the
whatever scheme we're using to manage
the replication and similarly as I
mentioned before we can't expect to deal
with bugs in the hardware the hardware
it computes incorrectly that's just
that's the end for us at least with this
kind of technique although you know that
said there are definitely hardware and
software bugs that that replication
might if you're lucky might be able to
cope it so if there's some unrelated
software running in your server and it
causes the server to crash maybe because
your kernel to panic and reboot or
something it has nothing to do with you
know with your with the service you're
replicating then that kind of failure
for us for your service will may well be
fail stop
you know the kernel will panic and the
backup replicas will take over similarly
some kinds of hardware errors can be
turned into fail stop errors for example
if you send a packet over the network
and the network corrupts it just flips a
bit in your packet that will almost
certainly be caught by the checksum on
the packet same thing for a disk block
if you write some data to disk and read
it back a month later you know maybe the
magnetic surface isn't perfect and you
know one of the best couple of bits were
wrong in the block as it's right back
it's actually error correcting
that up to a certain point will fix
errors in disk blocks that you'll be
turning you know random hardware errors
into as either correcting them if you're
super lucky or at least detecting them
and turning random corruption into a
detected fault which you know the
software then knows that something that
wrong and can turn it into a fail stop
fault by stopping executing or take some
other remedial action but in general we
really can only expect to handle fail
stop faults there's other limits to
replication to you know the the failures
in the if we have a primary in the back
of our two replicas or whatever we're
really assuming that failures in the two
are independent right if there tend to
have correlated failures then
replication is not going to help us so
for example if we're a big outfit and we
buy thousands of computers batches of
thousands of computers identical
computers from the same manufacturer and
we run you know our replicas is on all
on those computers we bought at the same
time from the same place that's a bit of
a risk
maybe because presumably if one of them
has a manufacturing defect in it there's
a good chance that the other ones do too
you know one of them's prone to
overheating because the manufacturer you
know didn't provide enough airflow well
it probably all had that problem and so
one of them overheats and dies it's a
good chance that the other ones will too
so that's one kind of correlated failure
you just have to be careful of another
one is that you know if there's an
earthquake and the city where our
datacenter is probably gonna take out
the whole data center you know we can
have all the replication we like inside
that data center it's not going to help
us because the failure caused by an
earthquake or a citywide power failure
or something the building burning down
is like it's correlated failure between
our replicas if they're on that building
so if we care about dealing with
earthquakes then we need to put our
replicas in maybe in just different
cities at least physically separate
enough that they have separate power
unlikely to be affected by the same
natural disaster
okay but that's all sort of hovering in
the background for this discussion where
we're talking about the technology you
might use another question about
replication is whether it's worthwhile
you may ask yourself gosh you know this
literally uses these replication schemes
use twice as much or three times as much
computer resources right we need to have
you know GFS had three copies of every
blocks we have to buy three times as much
disk space the paper for today
you know replicates just once but that
means we have twice as many computers
and CPUs and RAM it's all for expensive
like is that really worth it that
expense and you know that's not
something we can answer technically
right it's an economic question it
depends on the value of having an
available service you know if you're
running a bank and if the consequence is
the computer failing is that your
customer you can't serve your customers
and you can't generate revenue and your
customers all hate you then it may well
be worth it to blow you know an extra
ten or twenty thousand bucks on a second
computer so you can have a replica on
the other hand if you're me and you're
running the 6.824 web server I don't
consider it worthwhile to have a hot
backup of the 84 web server because the
consequences of failure are very low so
the whether the replication is
worthwhile on how many replicas you
ought to have and how much you're
willing to spend on it is all about how
much cost and inconvenience failure
would call it cause you all right this
paper sort of in the beginning mentions
as there's a couple of different
approaches to replication really
mentions two one two calls state
transfer and the other calls replicated
state machine most of the schemes we're
going to talk about in this class are
replicated state machines
it'll talk about both anyway the idea
behind state transferor's that if we
have two replicas of a server the way
you cause them to be to stay in sync
that is to be actual replicas so that
the backup can has everything it needs
to take over if the primary fails in a
state transfer scheme the way that works
is that the primary sends a copy of its
entire state that is for example the
contents of its RAM to the backup and
the backup just sort of stores the
latest state and so it's all there
the primary fails in the backup can
start executing with this last state it
got if the primary fails so this is all
about sending the state of the of the
primary and for today's if today's paper
worked as a state transfer system which
it doesn't then the state we'd be
talking about would be the contents of
the RAM the contents of the memory of
the primary so maybe every once while
the primary would just you know make a
big copy of its memory and send it
across the network to the backup you can
imagine if you wanted to be efficient
you know maybe you would only send the
parts of the memory that it's changed
since the last time you sent in memory
to the backup the replicated state
machine
this approach observes that most
services are most computer things we
want to replicate have some internal
operation that's deterministic except
when external input comes in right
ordinarily if there's no external
influences on a computer
it just executes one instruction after another
and what each instruction does is a
deterministic function of what's in the
memory and the registers of the computer
and it's only when external events intervene
that something unexpected may happen
like a packet arrives of a some random time
and that causes the server
to start doing something differently
so replicated state machine schemes
don't send the state between the replicas
instead they just send those
external events they just send maybe
from a primary to a backup again
just send things like arriving input from the
outside world that the backup needs to
know about
and the observation is that
if there are two computers and they start
from the same state and they see the
same inputs in the same order
or at the same time the two computers
will continue to be replicas of each
other and sort of execute identically
as long as they both see the same inputs at the same time
so this transfers probably memory
and this transfer some primary backup
just operations from clients or
external external inputs or external events
and the reason why
people tend to favor a replicated state machine
is that usually operations are
smaller than the state but this
the state of a server if it's a database
server might be the entire database
might be gigabytes whereas the
operations are just some clients sending
please read or write key 27
operations are usually small the states
usually large so replicate a state
machine usually looks attractive and
slight downside is that the schemes tend
to be quite a bit more complicated and
rely on sort of more assumptions about
how the computers operate whereas
this is a really heavy-handed
I'm just gonna send you my whole state sort of a
nothing to worry about
any questions about these strategies yes
well ok so the question is
suppose something went wrong with our scheme
and the backup was not actually
identical to the primary so
suppose we were running a GFS master
and it's the primary it just
handed out a lease to chunks server one
but because the two because
we've allowed the states of the primary
back to drift out of sync
the backup did not issue a lease to anybody
or even aware anybody had asked for lease
so now the primary thinks
chunks server one has lease for some chunk
the backup doesn't the primary fails
backup takes over right now chunks server
one thinks it has a lease for some chunk
but then the current master doesn't and
is happy to hand out the lease to some
other chunk server now we have two chunk
servers serving the same lease okay so
that's just a close to home example
but really almost any bad thing and
kind of I think you construct any bad
scenario by just imagining some service
that conpute the wrong answer because
the state's diverge
so you're asking about randomization
yeah oh y'all talk about this I'll talk
about this a bit later on but it is good
that the replicated state scheme
definitely makes the most sense when the
instructions that the primary and
backup are executing do the same thing
as long as there's no external events
right and that's almost true right
for an add instruction or something
yeah if the starting if the
registers and memory of the same and they
both execute an add instruction add instruction
has the same inputs in
the same outputs but they're in some
instructions as you point out that don't
like maybe there's an instruction that
gets the current time of day now
probably be executed at slightly
different times or an instruction that
gets the current processors unique ID
and a serial number it's going to yield
different answers
and the uniform answered the questions that
sound like this is that the primary does it
and sends the answer to the backup
and the backup does not execute that instruction
but instead at the point
where it would execute that instruction
it listens for the primary to tell it
what the right answer would be and just
sort of fakes that answer to the software
I'll talk about how
the VMware scheme does that okay
interestingly enough though
today's paper is all about a replicated state machine
you may have noticed that
today's paper only deals with uni-processors
and it's not that clear how
it could be extended to a multi-core and
a multi-core machine where the
interleavings of the instructions from
the two cores are
non-deterministic
so we no longer have this situation on a
multi-core machine where if we just let
the primary and backup execute they're
all else being equal they're
going to be the same because they won't
execute on multiple cores
VMware has since come out with a new possibly
completely different replication system
that does work on multi-core
and the new system appears to me to be using state transfer
instead of replicated state machine
because state transferred is
more robust in the face of
multi-core and parallelism
if you use the machine and send the memory over
that the memory image is just that
just is the state of the machine and
sort of it doesn't matter that there was
parallelism whereas the replicated state
machine scheme really has a problem with
the parallelism
on the other hand I'm guessing that this new
multi-core scheme is more expensive okay
all right so if we want to build a
replicated state machine scheme we got a
number of questions to answer
so we need to decide at what level we're gonna
replicate state right so what state
what do we mean by state we have to worry
about how closely synchronized the
primary and backup have to be right
because it's likely the primary will
execute a little bit ahead of the backup
after all it it's the primary that sees the inputs
so the backup almost
necessarily must lag over that gives
that means there's an opportunity if the
primary fails for the
backup not to be fully caught up
having the backup actually executes really in
lockstep with the primaries is expensive
because it requires a lot of chitchat
so a lot of designs a lot of
what people sweat about is how close the synchronization is
if the primary fails
or you know actually if the backup fails too
but it's more exciting if the primary fails
there has to be some scheme for
switching over and the clients have to know
oh gosh I instead of talking to the
old primary on server one I should now
be talking to the
the backup on server two all the clients
have to somehow figure this out
the switch over almost certainly it's almost
impossible maybe impossible to design a
cut over system in which no anomalies
are ever visible
in this sort of ideal world
if the primary fails we'd like nobody to ever notice
none of the clients to notice turns out
that's basically unattainable
so there's going to be anomalies during the cut over
and we've gotta figure out a way to
cope with them and finally if the one of
the two if one of our replicas fails
we really need to have a new replica right
if we have a two replicas and one fails
we're just living on borrowed time right
because the second replica may fail at some point
so we absolutely need to get
a new replica back online as fast as possible
so and that can be very
expensive the state is big
but the reason we like to replicate
a state machine was because we thought
state transfer would be expensive but
the two replicas in a replicated state
machine still need to have full state right
we just had a cheap way of keeping
them both in sync if we need to create a
new replica we actually have no choice
but state transfer to create the new replicas
the new replica needs to have a
complete copy of the state
so it's going to be expensive to create new replicas
and this is often people spending well
actually people spend a lot of time
worrying about all these questions and
we'll see them again as we look
at other replicated state machine schemes
so on the topic of what state to replicate
the today's paper has a very
interesting answer to this question
it replicates the full state of the machine
that is all of memory and all the
Machine registers it's like a very very
detailed replication scheme
just no difference at the even of the lowest
levels between the primary and the backup.
that's quite rare for replication
schemes
almost always you see something that's
more like GFS where GFS absolutely did
not replicate , you know they had
replication but it wasn't replicating
every single you know bit of memory
between the primaries and the backups.
it was replicating much more application level
(e.g.) table of chunks.
I had this abstraction of (GFS) , you know
chunks and chunk identifiers and that's
what it was replicating . it wasn't
replicating sort of everything else
wasn't going to the expense of
replicating every single other thing
in that machines we're doing okay as long
as they had the same sort of application
visible set of chunks . so most
replication schemes out there go the GFS
route in fact almost everything except
pretty much this paper and a few handful
of similar systems almost everything
uses application at some level
application level of replication because
it can be much more efficient because we
don't have to go to the we don't have to
go to the trouble of for example making
sure that interrupts occur at exactly
the same point in the execution of the
primary and backup GFS does not sweat
that at all but this paper has to do
because it replicates at such a low
level so most people build efficient
systems with applications specific
replication the consequence of that
though is that the replication has to be
built into the right into the
application right if you're getting a
feed of application level operations for
example you really need to have the
application participate in that because
some generic replication thing like
today's paper
doesn't really can't understand the
semantics of what needs to be replicated
so anyway so most teams are application
specific like GFS and every other paper
we're going to read on this topic
today's paper is unique in that it
replicates at the level of the machine
and therefore does not care what
software you run on it right it
replicates the low-level memory and
machine registers you can run any
software you like on it as long as it
runs on that kind of microprocessor
that's being represented this
replication scheme applies to the
software can be anything
and you know the downside is that it's
not that efficient necessarily the
upside is that you can take any existing
piece of software maybe you don't even
have source code for it or understand
how it works and you know do within some
limits you can just run it under this
under VMware's replication scheme and
it'll just work which is sort of magic
fault-tolerance wand for arbitrary
software all right now let me talk about
how this is VMware FT first of all
VMware is a virtual machine company
they're what their business is a lot of
their business is selling virtual
machine technology and what virtual
machines refer to is the idea of you
know you buy a single computer and
instead of booting an operating system
like Linux on the hardware you boot
we'll call a virtual machine monitor or
hypervisor on the hardware and the
hypervisor's job is actually to
simulate multiple multiple computers
multiple virtual computers on this piece
of hardware so the virtual machine
一个Linux实例
instance of Linux may be multiple
instances of Linux may be a Windows
machine you can the virtual machine
monitor on this one computer can run a
bunch of different operating systems you
know each of these as is itself some
sort of operating system kernel and then
applications so this is the technology
they're starting with and you know the
reason for this is that if you know you
need to it just turns out there's many
many reasons why it's very convenient to
kind of interpose this level of
indirection between the hardware and the
operating systems and means that we can
buy one computer and run lots of
different operating systems on it we can
have each if we run lots and lots of
little services instead of having to
have lots and lots of computers one per
service you can just buy one computer
and run each service in the operating
system that it needs I'm using these
virtual machines so this was their
starting point they already had this
stuff and a lot of sophisticated things
built around it at the start of
designing vmware ft so this is just
virtual machines um what the paper's
doing is that it's gonna set up one
machine or they did requires two
physical machines because there's no
point in running the primary and backup
software in different virtual machines
on the same physical machine because
we're trying to guard against hardware
failures so you're gonna to at least you
know you have two machines running their
virtual machine monitors and the primary
is going to run on one, the backup is on
the other so on one of these machines we
have a guest you know we only it might
be running a lot of virtual machines we
only care about one of them it's gonna
be running some guest operating system
and some sort of server application
maybe a database server, MapReduce master,
or something so I'll call this the
primary and there'll be a second machine
that you know runs the same virtual
machine monitor and an identical virtual
machine holding the backup so we have
the same whatever the operating system
is exactly the same and the virtual
machine is you know giving these guest
operating systems the primary and backup
a each range of memory and this memory
images will be identical or the goal is
to make them identical in the primary in
the backup we have two physical machines
each one of them running a virtual
machine guest with its own copy of the
service we care about we're assuming
that there's a network connecting these
two machines and in addition on this
local area network in addition on this
network there's some set of clients
really, they don't have to be clients
they're just maybe other computers that
our replicated service needs to talk
with some of them are clients
sending requests it turns out in this
paper there the replicated service
actually doesn't use a local disk and
instead assumes that there's some sort
of disk server that it talks to him
although it's a little bit hard to
realize this from the paper the scheme
actually does not really treat the
server particularly especially it's just
another external source of packets and
place that the replicated state machine
may send packets to not very much
different from clients okay so the basic
scheme is that the we assume that these
two replicas, the two virtual machines,
primary and backup, are exact
replicas . some client, you know database
client who knows who has some client of
our replicated server sends a request to
the primary and that really takes the
form of a network packet that's what
we're talking about that generates an
interrupt
and this interrupt actually goes to the
virtual machine monitor at least in the
first instance the virtual machine
monitor sees here's the input for
this replicated service and so the
virtual machine monitor does two things
one is it sort of simulates a network
packet arrival interrupt into the
primary guest operating system to
deliver it to the primary copy of the
application and in addition the virtual
machine monitor you know knows that this
is an input to a replicated virtual
machine and it's so it sends back out on
the network a copy of that packet to the
backup virtual machine monitor it also
gets it and backup virtual machine
monitor knows ha it is a packet for this
particular replicated state machine and
it also fakes a sort of network packet
arrival interrupt at the backup and
delivers the packet so now both the
primary and the backup have a copy this
packet they looks at, the same input you
know with a lot of details are gonna
process it in the same way and stay
synchronized
course the service is probably going to
reply to the client on the primary the
service will generate a reply packet and
send it on the NIC that the virtual
machine monitor is emulating and then
the virtual machine monitor will
we'll see that output packet on the
primary they'll actually send the reply
back out on the network to the client
because the backup is running exactly
the same sequence of instructions it
also generates a reply packet back to
the client and sends that reply packet
on its emulated NIC it's the virtual
machine monitor that's emulating that
network interface card and it says aha
you know the virtual machine monitor
says I know this was the backup only the
primary is allowed to generate output
and the virtual machine monitor drops
the reply packet so both of them see
inputs and only the primary generates
outputs as far as terminology goes the
paper calls this stream of input events
and other things, other events we'll talk
about from the stream is called the
logging Channel it all goes over the
same network presumably but these events
the primary send to the backup are called
log events on the log Channel
where the fault tolerance comes in is
that those the primary crashes what the
backup is going to see is that it stops
getting stuff on the stops getting log
entries a log entry stops getting log
entries on the logging channel and we
know it it turns out that the backup can
expect to get many per second because
one of the things that generates log
entries is periodic timer interrupts in
the in the primary each one of which
turns out every interrupt generates a
log entries into the backup these timer
interrupts are going to happen like 100
times a second so the backups can
certainly expect to see
a lot of chitchat on the logging Channel
if the primaries up if the primary
crashes then the virtual machine
monitored over here will say gosh you
know I haven't received anything on the
logging channel for like a second or
however long the primary must be dead or
or something and in that case when the
backup stop seeing log entries from the
primary the paper the way the paper
phrases it is that the backup goes live
and what that means is that it stops
waiting for these input events on the
logging Channel from the primary and
instead this virtual machine monitor
just lets this backup execute freely
without waiting for without being driven
by input events from the primary the vmm
does something to the network to cause
future client requests to go to the
backup instead of the primary and the
VMM here stops discarding the backup
personnel it's the primary not the
backup stops discarding output from this
virtual machine so now this or machine
directly gets the inputs and there's a
lot of produce output and now our backup
is taken over and similarly you know
that this is less interesting but has to
work correctly
if the backup fails a similar primary
has to use a similar process to abandon
the backup stop sending it events and
just sort of act much more like a single
non replicated server so either one of
them can go live if the other one
appears to be dead stops you know stops
generating network traffic
magic now it depends you know depends on
what the networking technology is I
think with the paper one possibility is
that this is sitting on Ethernet every
physical computer on the Internet or
really every NIC has a 48 bit unique ID
I'm making this up now the it could be
that in fact instead of each physical
computer having a unique ID each virtual
machine does and when the backup takes
over it essentially claims the primary's
Ethernet ID as its own and it starts
saying you know I'm the owner of that ID
and then other people on the ethernet
will start sending us packets that's my
interpretation the designers believed
they had identified all such sources and
for each one of them the primary does
whatever it is you know executes the
random number generator instruction or
takes an interrupt at some time the
backup does not and the back of virtual
machine monitor sort of detects any such
instruction and and intercepts that and
doesn't do it and he said the backup
waits for an event on the logging
Channel saying this instruction number
you know the random number was whatever
it was on the primary
At which?
yes yes
yeah the paper hints that they got Intel
to add features to the microprocessor to
support exactly this but they don't say
what it was okay
okay so on that topic the so far that
you know the story is sort of assumed
that as long as the backup to sees the
package from the clients it'll execute
in identically to the primary and that's
actually glossing over some huge and
important details so one problem is that
as a couple of people have mentioned
there are some things that are
non-deterministic now it's not the case
that every single thing that happens in
the computer is a deterministic function
of the contents of the memory of the
computer it is for a sort of straight
line code execution often but certainly
not always so worried about is things
that may happen that are not a strict
function of the current state that is
that might be different if we're not
careful on the primary and backup so
these are sort of non-deterministic
events that may happen so the designers
had to sit down and like figure out what
they all work and here are the ones
here's the kind of stuff they talked
about so one is inputs from external
sources like clients which arrive just
whenever they arrive right they're not
predictable there are no sense in which
the time at which a client request
arrives or its content is a
deterministic function of the services
state because it's not so these actually
this system is really dedicated to a
world in which services only talk over
the network and so the only really
basically the only form of input or
output in this system is supported by
this system seems to be network packets
coming and going so we didn't put
arrives at what that really means it's a
packet
arrives and what a packet really
consists of for us is the data in the
packet plus the interrupt
that's signaled that the packet had
arrived so that's quite important so
when a packet arrives
I'm ordinarily the NIC DMAs the packet
contents into memory and then raises an
interrupt which the operating system
feels and the interrupt happens at some
point in the instruction stream and so
both of those have to look identical on
the primary and backup or else we're
gonna have they're also executions gonna
diverge and so you know the real issue
is when the interrupt occurs exactly at
which instruction the interrupts happen
to occur and better be the same on the
primary in the backup otherwise their
execution is different and their states
are gonna diverge and so we care about
the content of the packet and the timing
of the interrupt and then as a couple of
people have mentioned there's a few
instructions that that behave
differently on different computers or
differently depending on something like
there's maybe a random number generator
instruction there's I get time-of-day
instructions that will yield different
answers have called at different times
and unique ID instructions another huge
source of non determinism which the
paper basically rules out is multi-core
parallelism this is a uni-process only
system there's no multi-core in this
world the reason for this is that if it
allowed multi-core then then the service
would be running on multiple cores and
the instructions of the service the rest
of you know the different cores are
interleaved in some way which is not
predictable and so really if we run the
same code on the on the backup in the
server if it's parallel code running on
a multi-core the tube interleave the
instructions in the two cores in
different ways the hardware will and
that can just cause
different results because you know
supposing the code and the two cores you
know they both asked for a lock on some
data well on the master you know
core one may get the lock before core two
on the slave just because of a tiny
timing difference core two may got the
lock first and the you know execution
results are totally different likely to
be totally different if different
threads get the lock
so multi-core is the grim source among
non-determinisms just totally
outlawed in this papers world and indeed
like as far as I can tell the techniques
are not really applicable the service
can't use multi-core parallel parallelism
the hardware is almost
certainly multi-core parallel
but that's the hardware sitting underneath the
virtual machine monitor
the machine that the virtual machine monitor exposes to
one of the guest operating systems that
runs the primary backup that emulated
virtual machine is a unicore
is a uni-processor machine in this paper
and I'm guessing there's not an easy way for them
to adapt this design to multi-core
virtual machines
okay so these are really
it's these events that go over the logging channel
and so the format of a log record
a log entry they don't quite say
but I'm guessing that there's
really three things in a log entry
the instruction number at which
the event occurred
because if you're delivering an interrupt or
input or whatever it better be delivered
at exactly the same place in the primary and backup
so we need to know the
instruction number and by instruction number
I mean the number of
instructions since the machine booted
not the instruction address but like
oh we're executing the four billion and
79th instructions since boot
so log entry is gonna have an instruction number
for an interrupt, for input it's
going to be the instruction at which the
interrupt was delivered on the primary
and for a weird instruction like get time of day
it's going to be the
instruction number of the instruction of
the get time of day or whatever instruction
that was executed on the primary
so that the backup
knows where to where to call this event to occur
okay so there's gonna be a type
network input whatever, weird instruction
and then there's gonna be data
for a packet arrival it's gonna
be the packet data, for one of these
weird instructions it's going to be the
result of the instruction
when it was executed on the primary
so that the backup virtual machine can sort of
fake the instruction and supply that same
result
okay so as an example the
both of these operating systems guest operating system
assumes requires that the
hardware in this case emulated hardware
virtual machine has a timer that ticks
say a hundred times a second
and causes interrupts to the operating system and
that's how the operating system keeps
track of time it's by counting these timer interrupts
so the way that plays
out here, so the timers have to
happen at exactly the same place in the primary and backup
otherwise they don't
execute the same and diverge
so what really happens is that
there's a timer on the physical machine
that's running the FT virtual machine monitor
and the timer on the physical
machine ticks and delivers an interrupt
a timer interrupt to the virtual machine
monitor on the primary
the virtual machine monitor at the
appropriate moment stops the execution of the primary
writes down the
instruction number that it was at
instruction since boot
and then delivers sort of fake emulates and
interrupts into the guest operating
system in the primary at that
instruction number
saying oh you know you're emulating the timer hardware just
ticked there's the interrupt
and then the
primary virtual machine monitor sends
that instruction number which the
interrupt happened to the backup
the backup of course it's virtual
machine monitor is also taking timer
interrupts from its physical timer
and it's not giving them it's not giving
its real physical timer interrupts
to the backup operating system. it's just ignoring them
when the
log entry for the primary's timer
interrupts arrives here
then the backup virtual machine monitor will arrange
with the CPU and this requires special
CPU support to cause the physical
machine to interrupt at the same
instruction number
at the timer interrupts tapped into the primary
at that point the virtual
machine monitor gets control again from the guest
and then fakes the timer
interrupts into the backup operating system
now exactly the same
instruction number as it occurred on the primary
well yeah so the observation is
that this relies on the CPU
having some special hardware in it
where the vmm can tell the hardware， CPU please
interrupt a thousand instructions from now
and then the vmm where so that
it'll interrupt at the
right instruction number the same
instruction as the primary did
and then the vmm just tells the cpu to
resume executing again in the backup
and exactly a thousand instructions later
the CPU will force an interrupt into the
virtual machine monitor
and that that's special hardware but it turns out it's
on all Intel chips so it's not
it's not that special anymore
15 years ago it was exotic now it's totally normal
and it turns out there's
a lot of other uses for it like um if
you want to do profiling you wanna do
CPU time profiling what you'd really like
or one way to do CPU time profiling
is to have the microprocessor interrupt
every thousand instructions right
and this is the hardware that's this
Hardware also this is the same hardware
that would cause the microprocessor to
generate an interrupt every thousand instructions
so it's a very natural sort
of gadget to want in your CPU
all right yes
what if the backup gets ahead of the primary
we standing above
know that the primary is
about to take an interrupt at the millionth instruction
but the backup has
already executed the million
and first instruction
if we let this happen it's gonna be too
late to deliver the interrupts
if we let the backup execute ahead of the primary
it's going to be too late to deliver the
interrupts at the same point in the
primary instruction stream and the
backup instruction stream
so we cannot let that happen we cannot let the
backup get ahead of the primary in execution
and the way VMware FT does
that is that the backup virtual machine monitor
actually keeps a
buffer of waiting events that have
arrived from the primary
and it will not let the backup execute unless
there's at least one event in that buffer
and if there's one event in that buffer
then it will know from the instruction number
the place at which it's got a force the
backup to stop executing
so always the backup is executing with the
CPU being told exactly where the next
stopping point the next instruction
number of a stopping point is
because the backup only executes if it has an
event here that tells it where to stop next
so that means it starts up after the primary
because the backup can't
even start executing until the primary
has generated the first event
and that event has arrived at the backup
so the backup sort of always one event
basically behind the at least one event
behind the primary
and if it's slower for some other whatever reason maybe
there's other stuff running on that
physical machine
then the backup might get multiple events behind
the primary
alright there's a one little piece of
mess about arriving the specific case of arriving packets
ordinarily when a
packet arrives from a network interface card
if we weren't running a virtual machine
the network interface card would
DMA(Direct Memory Access) the packet content into the memory
of the computer that it's attached to
sort of as the data arrives from the
network interface card
and that means you should never write software like this
but it could be that the
operating system that's running on a
computer might actually see the data of
a packet as its DMA or copied from the
network interface card into memory right
this is and you know we don't
know what operating this system is
designed so that it can support any operating system
and gosh maybe there is
an operating system that watches
arriving packets in memory as they're
copied into memory
so we can't let that happen
because if the primary happens to be playing that trick
it's gonna see
you know if we allowed the network interface card to directly DMA incoming packets into the memory of the primary
the primary we don't have any control over the exact timing of
and so we're not going to know sort of at what times the primary did or didn't observe data from the packet arriving
and so what that means is that in fact the NIC copies incoming packets into private memory of the virtual machine monitor
and then the network interface card interrupts the virtual machine monitor and says oh a packet has arrived
at that point the virtual machine monitor will suspend the primary
and remember what instruction number had suspended at
copy the entire packet into the primaries memory while the primary suspended and not looking at this copy
and then emulate a network interface card interrupt into the primary
and then send the packet and the instruction number to the backup
the backup will also suspend the backup rope
you know virtual machine monitor will spend the backup at that instruction number
copy the entire packet and again to the back-up is guaranteed not to be watching the data arrive
and then fakin interrupts at the same instruction numbers of the primary
and this is the something the bounce buffer mechanism explained in the paper
okay yeah the the only instructions and that result in logging channel traffic or are weird instructions which are rare
no its instructions that might yield a different result if executed on the primary and backup
like instruction to get the current time of day or current processor number
or ask how many instructions have been executed or
and those actually turn out to be relatively rare
there's also one them to get random tasks when some machines
to ask or a hardware generated random number for cryptography or something
and but those are not everyday instructions
most instructions like add instructions they're gonna get the same result on primary and backup
exactly right each network packet just it's packaged up and forwarded as it is as a network packet
and is interpreted by the tcp/ip stack on both you know
so I'm expecting 99.99% of the logging channel traffic to be incoming packets
and only a tiny fraction to be results from special non-deterministic instructions
and so we can kind of guess what the traffic load is likely to be for for a server that serves clients
basically it's a copy of every client packet
and then we'll sort of know what the logging channel how fast the logging channel has to be
it's worth talking a little bit about how output works
and in this system really the only what output basically means only is sending packets
that client send requests in as network packets the response goes back out as network packets
and there's really no other form of output
as I mentioned the you know both primary and backup compute the output packet they want to send
and that sort of asks that simulated mix to send the packet it's really sent on the primary
and simply discard it the output packet discarded on the backup
okay but it turns out is a little more complicated than that
so supposing we're what we're running is a some sort of simple database server
and the operation the client operation that our database server supports is increment
and ideas the client sends an increment requests the database server increments the value and sends back the new value
so maybe on the primary well let's say everything's fine so far
and the primary backup both have value 10 in memory and that's the current value at the counter
and some client on the local area network sends a you know an increment request
to the primary that packet is you know delivered to the primary it's you know
it's executed the primary server software and the primary
says oh you know current values 10 I'm gonna change to 11
and send a you know response packet back to the client saying saying 11
mentioned gonna supposed to be sent to the backup will also be processed here it's going to change this 10 to 11 also
generate a reply and we'll throw it away that's what's supposed to happen the output
however you also need to ask yourself what happens if there's a failure at an awkward time
if you should always in this class should always ask yourself
what's the most awkward time to have a failure and what would happen you to failure occurred then so
suppose the primary does indeed generate the reply here back to the client
but the client the primary crashes just after sending the report its reply to the client
and furthermore and much worse it turns out that you know this is just a network it doesn't guarantee to deliver packets
let's suppose this log entry on the logging channel got dropped also when the when the primary died
so now the state of play is the client received a reply saying 11
but the backup did not get the client request so its state is still 10
no now the backup takes over because it's seized the primary is dead and
this client or maybe some other client sends an increment request a new backup
and now it's really processing these requests and so the new backup when it gets the next increment requests
you know it's now going to change its state to 11
and generate a second 11 response
maybe the same client maybe to a different client
which if the clients compare notes or if it's the same client it's just obviously cannot have happened I didn't
so you know because we have to support unmodified software that does not damn
that there's any funny business of replication going on
that means we do not have the opportunity to
you know you can imagine the client could go
you know we could change the client to realize
something funny it happened with the fault tolerance and do I don't know what
but we don't have that option here
because this whole system really only makes sense if we're running unmodified software
so so this was a big this is a disaster
we can't have let this happen does
anybody remember from the paper how they prevent this from happening
the output rule yeah so you want to do you know
yeah so the output rules is the their solution to this problem
and the idea is that the client he's not allowed to generate you know and
generate any output the primary's not allowed to generate any output
and what we're talking about now is this output here
until the backup acknowledges that it has received all log records up to this point
so the real sequence at the primary then let's now undone crash the primary
go back to them starting at 10 the
real sequence now when the output rule is that
the input arrives at the time the input arrives
that's when the virtual machine monitor sends a copy of the input to the backup
so the the sort of time at which this log message with the input
is sent is before strictly before the primary generates the output sort of obvious
then after firing this log entry off across a network and now it's heading towards the backup
but I'd have been lost might not
the virtual machine monitor delivers a request to the primary server software it generates the output
so now the replicated you know the primary has actually generated change the state 211
and generated an output packet that says eleven
but the virtual machine monitor says oh wait a minute we're not allowed to generate that output
until all previous log records have been acknowledged by the backup
so you know this is the most recent previous log message
so this output is held by the virtual machine monitor
until the this log entry containing the input packet from the client
is delivered to the virtual machine monitor and buffered by the virtual machine monitor
but do not necessarily execute it
it may be just waiting for the backup to get to that point in the instruction stream
and then the virtual machine monitor here will send an ACK packet back saying yes I did get that input
and when the acknowledgment comes back
only then will the virtual machine monitor here release the packet out onto the network
and so the idea is that if the client could have seen the reply
then necessarily the backup must have seen the request and at least buffered it
and so we no longer get this weird situation
in which a client can see a reply but then there's a failure and a cut over
and the replica didn't know anything about that reply
if the you know there's also a situation maybe this message was lost
and if this log entry was lost and then the primary crashes
well since it hadn't been delivered so the backup hadn't sent the ACK
that means if the primary crashed
this log entry was brought in the primary crashed
it must have crashed before the virtual machine monitor release the output packet
and for this client couldn't have gotten the reply
and so it's not in a position to spot any irregularities
there we have the output rule
brennon see
I don't know paper doesn't mention how the virtual machine monitor is implemented
I mean it's pretty low level stuff because
it's sitting there allocating memory and figuring page tables
and talking to device drivers and intercepting instructions
and understanding what instructions the guest was executing
so we're talking about low-level stuff what language is written in traditionally C or C++
but I don't actually know
okay this of the primary has to delay at this point
waiting for the backup to say that it's up to date
this is a real performance thorn in the side of just about every replication scheme
this sort of synchronous wait where the we can't let the primary get too far ahead of the backup
because if the primary failed while it was ahead
that would be the backup lagging
lagging behind clients right
so just about every replication system has this problem that
at some point the primary has to stall waiting for the backup
and it's a real limit on performance
even if the machines are like side-by-side and adjacent racks
it's still you know we're talking about a half a millisecond or something
to send messages back and forth with a primary stalled
and if we wanna like withstand earthquakes or citywide power failures
you know the primary in the backup have to be in different cities
that's probably five milliseconds apart
every time we produce output if we replicate in the two replicas in different city
every packet that it produces this output
has to first wait the five milliseconds or whatever to have the last log entry get to the backup
and have the acknowledgment come back and then we can release a path packet
and you know for sort of low intensity services that's not a problem
but if we're building a you know database server that we would like to
you know that if it weren't for this could process millions of requests per second
then that's just unbelievably damaging for performance
and this is a big reason why people you know
if they possibly can use a replication scheme
that's operating at a higher level and kind of understands the semantics of operations
and so it doesn't have to stall on every packet
you know it could stall on every high level operation or even notice that well
you know read-only operations don't have to stall at all
it's only write or just stall at something
but you have to there has to be an application level replication scheme to to realize that
you're absolutely right
so the observation is that you don't have to stall the execution of the primary
you only have to hold the output
and so maybe that's not as bad as it could be
but nevertheless it means that every you know in a service
that could otherwise have responded in a couple of microseconds to the client
you know if we have to first update the replicas in the next city
we turn to you know 10 micro second interaction into it 10 millisecond interactions possibly
if you have vast numbers of clients submitting concurrent requests
then you may may be able to maintain high throughput even with high latency
but you have to be lucky to or very clever designer to get that
that's a great idea
but if you log in the memory of the primary
that log will disappear when the primary crashes
or that's usual semantics of a server failing is that
you lose everything inside the box like the contents of memory
or you know if even if you didn't
if the failure is that somebody unplugged the power cable accidentally from the primary
even if the primary just has battery backed up RAM or I don't know what
you can't get at it
all right the backup can't get at it
so in fact this system does log the output and the place it logs it is in the memory of the backup
and in order to reliably log it there you have to observe the output rule and wait for the acknowledgment
so it's entirely correct idea just can't use the primary's memory for it
say it again
that's a clever idea I'd
and so the question is maybe input should go to the primary but output should come from the backup
I completely haven't thought this through
that might work that
I don't know that's interesting
yeah maybe I will
one possibility this does expose though is that
the situation you know maybe the a primary crashes after its output is released
so the client does receive the reply
then the primary crashes
the backups input is still in this event buffer
in the virtual machine monitor of the backup
it hasn't been delivered to the actual replicated service
when the backup goes live after the crash of the primary
the backup first has to consume all of the sort of log records that are lying around
that it hasn't consumed yet has to catch up to the primary
otherwise it won't take over with the same state
so before the backup can go live it actually has to consume all these entries
the last entry is presumably is the request from the client
so the backup will be live after after it
after the interrupt that delivers the request from the client
and that means that the backup well you know increment its counter to eleven
and then generate an output packet and since it's live at this point
it will generate the output packet and the client will get two eleven replies
which is also if it if that really happened would be anomalous
like possibly not something that could happen if there was only one server
the good news is that almost certainly
or the almost certainly the client is talking to this service using TCP
and that this is the request and the response go back and forth on a TCP Channel
the when the backup takes over
the backup since the state is identical to the primaries it knows all about that TCP connection
and whether all the sequence numbers are and whatnot
and when it generates this packet
it will generate it with the same TCP sequence number as an original packet
and the TCP stack on the client will say oh wait a minute that's a duplicate packet
we'll discard the duplicate packet at the TCP level
and the user level software will just never see this duplicate
and so this system really you know
you can view this as a kind of accidental or clever trick
but the fact is for any replication system where cutover can happen
which is to say pretty much any replication system
it's essentially impossible to design them
in a way that they are guaranteed not to generate duplicate output
basically you know you well you can err on either side
I'm not even either not generate the output at all which
would be bad which would be terrible
or you can generate the output twice on a cutover
that's basically no way to generate it guaranteed generated only once
everybody errors on the side or possibly generating duplicate output
and that means that at some level the client side of all replication schemes
need some sort of duplicate detection scheme
here we get to use TCP s that we didn't have TCP that would have to be something else
maybe application level sequence numbers or I don't know what
and you'll see all of this
and actually you'll see versions of
essentially everything I've talked about like the output rule for example in labs 2 & 3
you'll design your own replicated state machine
yes
yes to the first part
so the scenario is
the primary sends the reply
and then either the primary send the close packet
or the client closes the connect the TCP connection after it receives the primary's reply
so now there's like no connection on the client side
but there is a connection on the backup side
and so now the backup
so the backup consumes the very last log entry that as the input is now live
so we're not responsible for replicating anything at this point right
because the backup now live there's no other replica as the primary died
so there's no like if if we don't if the backup fails to execute in log step with the primary
that's fine actually
because the primary is is dead and we do not want to execute in log step with it
okay so the primer is now not it's live
it generates an output on this TCP connection that isn't closed yet from the backup point of view
this packet arrives with the client on a TCP connection
that doesn't exist anymore from the clients point of view
like no big whoopee on the client right
he's just going to throw away the packet as if nothing happened the application won't no
the client may send a reset
something like a TCP error or whatever packet
back to the backup and the backup does something or other with it
but it doesn't matter b
ecause we're not diverging from anything
because there's no primary to diverge from
you can just handle a stray we said however it likes
and what it'll in fact do is basically ignore
but there's no now the backup has gone live there's just no
we don't owe anybody anything as far as replication
yeah
well you can bet since the backups memory image is identical to the primaries image
that they're sending packets with the very same source TCP number
and they're very same everything
they're sending bit for bit identical packets
you know at this level the server's don't have IP addresses
or for our purposes
the virtual machines you know the primary in the back up virtual machines have IP addresses
but the the physical computer and the vmm are transparent to the network
it's not entirely true but it's basically the case that
the virtual machine monitor in the physical machine
don't really have identity of their own on the network
because you can configure that then that way instead these they're not
you know the virtual machine with a sewing operating system in its own TCP stack
it doesn't IP address underneath there an address and all this other stuff
which is identical between the primary in the backup
and when it sends a packet
it sends it with the virtual machines IP address and Ethernet address
and those bits least in my mental model are just simply passed through on to the local area network
it's exactly what we want
and so I think he doesn't generate exactly the same packets
that the primary would have generated
there's maybe a little bit of trickery you know what the we
if this is these are actually plugged into an Ethernet switch
into the physical machines maybe it wasn't in two different ports of an Ethernet switch
and we'd like the Ethernet switch to change its mind about
which of these two machines that delivers packets with replicated services Ethernet address
and so there's a little bit of funny business there
for the most part they're just generating identical packets
so let me just send them out
okay so another little detail I've been glossing over is that
I've been assuming that the primary just fails or the backup just fails
that is fail stop right
but that's not the only option
another very common situation that has to be dealt with is
if the two machines are still up and running and executing
but there's something funny happen on the network
that causes them not to be able to talk to each other
but to still be able to talk to some clients
so if that happened if the primary backup couldn't talk to each other
but they could still talk to the clients
they would both think oh the other replicas dead
I better take over and go live
and so now we have two machines going live with this service
and now you know they're no longer sending each other log events or anything
they're just diverging
maybe they're accepting different client inputs and changes are stayed in different ways
so now we have a split brain disaster
if we let the primary in the backup go live
because it was a network that has some kind of failure instead of these machines
and the way that this paper solves it I mean
is by appealing to an outside authority to make the decision about
which of the primary of the backup is allowed to be live
and so
it they're you know it turns out that their storage is actually not on local disk
this almost doesn't matter
but their storage is on some external disk server
and as well as being in this server as a like totally separate service
there's nothing to do with disks
there this server happens to abort this test and set
test and set service over the network where you
you can send a test and set request to it
and there's some flag it's keeping in memory
and it'll set the flag and return what the old value was
so both primary and backup have to sort of acquire this test and set flag
it's a little bit like a lock
in order to go live they both may be send test and set requests at the same time
to this test and set server
the first one gets back a reply that says oh the flag used to be zero
now it's one this second request to arrive
the response from the test and set server is
Oh actually the flag was already one when your request arrived
so so basically you're not allowed to be primary
and so this this test and set server
and we can think of it as a single machine
is the arbitrator that decides which of the two should go live
if they both think the other ones dead due to a network partition
any questions about this mechanism
you're busted
yeah if the test and set server should be dead at the critical moment when
and so actually even if there's not a network partition
under all circumstances in which
one or the other of these wants to go live because it thinks the others dead
even when the other one really is dead
the one that wants to collide still has to acquire the test and set lock
because one of like the deep rules of 6.824 game is that
you cannot tell whether or another computer is dead or not
all you know is that you stopped receiving packets from it
and you don't know whether it's because the other computer is dead
or because something has gone wrong with the network between you and the other computer
so all the backup ceases well I've stuck in packets
maybe the primary is dead maybe it's live
primary probably sees the same thing
so if there's a network partition
they certainly have to ask the Test-and-Set server
but since they don't know if it's a network partition
they have to ask the test and set server regardless of whether it's a partition or not
so anytime either wants to collide
the test and set server also has to be alive
because they always have to acquire this test and set lock
so the test and set server sounds like a single point of failure
they were trying to build a replicated fault tolerant whatever thing
but in the end you know we can't failover unless unless this is alive so
that's a bit of a bummer
I'm guessing though
I'm making a strong guess that the test and set server is actually
itself a replicated service and is fault tolerant right
it's almost certainly I mean these people of VMware
where they're like happy to sell you a million dollar highly available storage system
that uses enormous amounts of replication internally
um since the test and set thing is on there dis server
I'm I'm guessing it's replicated too
and the stuff you'll be doing in lab 2 in lab 3 is more than powerful enough
for you to build your own fault-tolerant test and set server
so this problem can easily be eliminated