you
alright let's get started today I want
to talk about
stack and the reason we're looking at
this paper is that it touches on three
questions that I find quite interesting
one is maybe at the lowest level how to
build a naming system or really a public
key infrastructure that maps from names
to public keys and this is like a very
important question nobody has ever
really figured out a convincing way to
build a general-purpose global public
key infrastructure or PKI so any
progress in this area with the is
interesting another reason I'm
interested in block stack is that it's a
non cryptocurrency use of a blockchain
you know so it's just an interesting
question whether block chains are useful
for anything other than than financial
stuff and finally and you know maybe
most interestingly block sects really a
proposal for a very different
architecture for how Internet services
or really web sites how websites
ought to be constructed very different
from the way they're constructed now is
quite different properties and you know
the idea is that maybe the the kind of
approach brock sack
takes might yield websites that are are
better you know in some ways than
current web sites now blocks likes a
real system there's a company that's
developing it that's in use by some
applications i'm just have some users
however it's really you know you should
view it as moral work-in-progress then
kind of this is the final answer they've
been developing it and making it better
over some years now i don't think it's
really to the point where very many
people would decide to abandon the way
they build websites now and switch to
block stack but it's very important that
somebody out there is exploring how
things could be different and better and
block stack is one of a number of
different projects that are trying to
push in a different direction for the
overall architecture of web sites all
right so the the pitch from block stack
is that people ought to be building
decent
applications so what does decentralize
mean sort of an idea that's been in the
air for a couple years now I think maybe
the best summary is that it's
applications that are built in a way
that moves ownership of data out of
centrally controlled websites you know
like ordinary web servers and one way or
another puts control of users
information more into the users own
hands so that it's sort of realistic to
say that users actually own their own
data instead of you know Facebook or
Gmail or whoever sort of essentially
owning their data for them the success
and the interesting properties of
Bitcoin have been a lot of what's driven
the recent activity in this area it's
kind of an old idea dates back at least
appeared appear on schemes like Nutella
and Napster from around 20 years ago and
further back than that but Bitcoin
really prompted people to think hard
about this and to sort of have a bit
more faith that these kinds of ideas
could be realized all right so I want to
kind of outline first what a sort of
centralized typical you know current web
site looks like talk a bit about why
some people aren't really pleased with
the way current websites work and then
outline how things might work under a
decentralized scheme like block stack so
this is really current websites the view
is you got a much users sitting in front
of browsers and there's a internet they
all talk to the internet you have some
website out there you know maybe it's
say Gmail or something and Gmail has a
bunch of web servers that are owned by
Gmail right owned by whatever the web
services and sitting behind the web
servers is some kind of database
it's kind of familiar picture for us
through these individual users this
database holds the users data like if
you use Gmail you know your you know
user ones Gmail is sitting in Gmail's
database somewhere you know this is a
database server the Gmail owns and
that's control over the kind of logic
for how Gmail operates essentially sits
in the web servers that own bio are
owned by Gmail and sort of talk to the
database to get out of your data alright
so there's like totally nothing
surprising here and you know this is the
way almost every website works this is
often some JavaScript or something and
sitting in the users browsers but all
the kind of critical stuff is sitting in
web servers or some kind of servers that
the website yawns you know so four
different websites the day on the
database is gonna be things like blog
posts or mail or you know comments you
post on other people's reddit or
something or maybe it's your photos your
calendar my is your medical records or
something there's a lot of data that's
out there at various different websites
that is in some sense you know the users
data like it's really the users Gmail
but gosh it's Gmail or that has control
over it or reddit that has control over
the users comments and other people's
articles
now this setups been SuperDuper
successful it's actually and one of the
reasons to sit it's extremely easy to
program you know all the logic hears and
running and servers controlled by Gmail
they can talk to these databases trough
in things like sequel databases that
very flexible query interfaces there's
like no restrictions on what data can be
accessed like you know so supposing this
is a eBay that's running here you know
the users bids are sitting in eBay's
database server now the bids are quite
private right if I'm bidding on
something I don't want other users to
see it but there's no restrictions on
what eBay's web servers can look at they
can all look at the bids in the in their
own database they can look at other
people's bids find the highest bid
there's really no restrictions so it's
very very convenient
for web developers and is very
successful and so from that point of
view we should be you know skeptical
that anything else could possibly be
this successful or overtake it but the
reason why you might not think this
current setup is perfect well there's a
bunch of reasons that users might be
dissatisfied one is that if I store my
mail in Gmail I really have to use
Gmail's interface to get at it
you know maybe they provide some other
ways of getting at it but I generally
don't have a lot of freedom like Gmail
sets the rules for how I get at my own
email right so I might be a little bit
irritated it's my email but you know I
don't get to choose what interface I use
I can't just use any software Lee pretty
much has to be software that Gmail
provides or Gmail supports for
situations like maybe Facebook where
other people might sometimes see my data
is really the website that gets to set
the rules for who gets access to my data
or how if at all I can control that
access and websites often are bit murky
about their promises about how they
enforce this stuff and again if it's the
users data like if it's my photos or my
posts or something it's really kind of
not that great that I don't have too
much control over what the website can
do with it another thing that people
complain about with the current set up
is that the website can sniff on my
stuff like Gmail wants to look through
my mail they might have good reasons for
maybe they were training their spam
generators so that's okay but you know
maybe looking at my email to think about
showing me advertisements or to you know
tell their advertising customers what
people are interested in these days
worse the there's a chance that some of
the employees who work at the web site
are corrupt and maybe snooping on
people's data for personal reasons so
that maybe the company maybe the company
that runs the website is perfectly
aboveboard but can't necessarily sit
claim that it's not always true that all
the employees are or following all the
rules anyway so people have a lot
kind of you know or some people have
reservations about the way the current
system works at a kind of more design
technical level one way to view what's
going on here is that the main interface
here is between the entire website and
the browser's so there's it's HTML
that's flowing back and forth between
here typically the websites and the
database are sort of integrated on this
side of the interface and all the
browser really gets to see often is this
HTML kind of final packaged form of the
data and you know it's a very user
interface oriented representation hTML
is and sort of Nod has nothing to say
about you know Dave the data itself or
how the data is controlled and the much
more interesting interface and where
this you know a whole discussion is kind
of going is that this is a much more
interesting interface because it's much
closer to the data but in the standard
setup there's no real boundary there
though this is sort of the internal
business how this works is the internal
business of the website all right so
that's the existing plan the plan the
kind of plan that block stack is
proposing and so there's a number of
kind of ideas for how decentralized apps
might work this is kind of one of them
so I'm not gonna call it block stack yet
because it's it's kind of much a very
simplified version we'll just say it's a
decentralized architecture and here the
game is that you know we still have a
bunch of users and users run you know
iPads or browsers or something
but we're gonna in this new
decentralized scheme we're gonna put all
of the app code is gonna run in the
client machines in the users machines
and so this is much more like a sort of
traditional or it's like you know
downloading an app from the app store on
an iPad or buying sort of old-style PC
hardware like buying a copy of Microsoft
Word this just runs on your laptop just
buy some software you run on your laptop
so no longer running the application
code in web servers well you know if all
you want to do is use data on your
laptop your own data on your own laptop
and then we're done but what's really
interesting about you know web-based
what about internet based applications
is that you can store your data in the
cloud and that means you can if you have
multiple devices which most people do
you can get at your data from any of
your devices from your maybe your iPhone
as well as your laptop and if you've
stored data in the cloud somehow that
means you can share data with other
people and build multi-user applications
like you know eBay maybe your reddit or
who knows what shared calendars so the
other half of the decentralized vision
is that there's going to be a storage
system some sort of cloud storage system
out there by which we mean I mean some
sort of service that you can buy maybe
you know from Amazon AWS or
who-knows-where which was just store
data for you you can stick data in it
it's your data they store for you back
it up
dumi hopefully some sort of access
control so whether people can't get at
it and then you can retrieve it later
from any of your devices and so now if
we're building some sort of you know for
single user applications like you know I
just need to edit some documents but I
want to keep them in the cloud you know
maybe user one is buying storage from
this storage server maybe it's Amazon
and user two is buying storage from
maybe Google's cloud storage system
for my own data I just talked to my own
my application code talks across the
internet to the service storage service
that I buy storage from presumably pay
for it myself and user to talk similarly
to their storage service but if we run
applications that are built to allow
users to share data then there's the
possibility that if I know how to talk
to you to storage service I can run an
application that reads data that they
allow me to read as well so you know if
you wanted to build some sort of a
Facebook like thing on this the
application would know who my friends
are and reach out to my friends storage
looking for updates or photos or who
knows what that my friends have stored
in their own storage so that means I
instead of contacting with Facebook's
website instead in his new model I would
download an app from Facebook and run it
and that app would sort of know how to
find my friends and look at the data
that they are storing and you know if my
friend uploads a photo to their storage
it's really still it's their storage
they're paying for it it's their photo
they can use it with Facebook or they
could use it with other applications too
because the applications are really
quite separate now from the from the
data instead of being combined in the
existing architecture all right so now
sort of a technical level the this is
now the storage interface is now the
main interface so now we have some sort
of put get or readwrite or who knows
what interface as the main interface
it's no longer HTML it's really a
primary interface we were worried about
it's the storage style interface which
is a much nicer interface to write
applications to then HTML it's
furthermore as I mentioned there's a
much in this architecture where users
really own and pay for an organizing on
storage there's a much clearer notion of
data being actually owned by the user
and controlled by the user much like you
own the data on your laptop or in your
Athena
as you ones account here in the storage
service of course there's a number of
but you know now we're very interested
in the design of the storage system
because now this is instead of being
sort of hidden away inside websites this
is now the primary interface in the
system so we care a lot about how it's
designed so first of all it's quite
critical that it be a Internet service
out in the cloud so we can get at it get
our data from from any of our devices it
really needs to be general-purpose that
all the application codes here so we
don't now in this architecture really
get to have applications specific code
at all on the server side because the
sort of servers aren't don't really have
anything directly to do with
applications so we needed a
general-purpose interface that's
powerful enough for to let us do
whatever we need which is a little bit
difficult to design we now have the
storage has to be paid for and now
really the most obvious person to pay
for it is the user themselves now maybe
they're willing to do that maybe they're
not we'd really like to have this
sharing but we also want to have private
data and maybe we only want to share our
data with certain other people so we
need some reason so the storage
interface in the storage system one way
or another needs reasonably powerful
sharing and permission access control
systems a more subtle issue is that I
may run multiple apps some of which I
don't trust right if I just download
some multi-user game from the internet
you know maybe I don't want it to be
able to look at my email while I'm
playing that game so that means that as
well as having a notion of sort of this
user with this users permission we may
want to have kind of subsidiary
permissions where we can talk about not
just this user as a whole but this user
when running an application to has
certain permissions maybe just game
files this user when running application
one is allowed to get at the users email
as well
alright then interestingly in their
notices that this storage interface it
says not as much of a stretch as it
might have seen say 10 or 20 years ago
because there's a number of storage
services out there that are not unlike
this like Amazon s3 very widely used and
while it's missing some of the things we
would need here it's definitely a public
storage system you can buy storage you
can let other people use your storage
you know doesn't have all that access
control we'd like but it's not too far
from what's needed here and indeed
today's papers observes that they can
layer their storage system on top of one
of a number of different existing
storage systems Dropbox is also it's
another kind of candidate for something
it's like this and therefore this is not
as sort of pie in the sky as it might
seem ok so what would the point of this
kind of architecture be why would
anybody care the people who might care
are the users this this might give users
more more control of their data it may
make it easier for users to switch
applications like if I've uploaded a
bunch of photos and I'm using one photo
organization app or photo editing app
since my photos are totally separate
from me from the app I could switch
photo apps and maybe still use all my
same old set of photos that I already
have stored it may be easier in this
architecture to have applications that
look at multiple kinds of data you know
maybe it'd be nice that my email system
be able to look at my calendar and the
other way around may be nice to be able
to write backup software they could
backup all of my data no matter what it
was
periodically maybe I'd like to have a
sort of general-purpose file browser
which would allow me to look at all of
my data and none of this is possible or
convenient and the current architecture
but it's all seems like within reach now
that we've kind of concentrated all the
users data into storage that that they
own and finally there may well be
advantages since in terms of privacy and
snooping
instead of entrusting my data to a web
service that who knows what it's doing
with it if we play our cards right we
can use encryption these applications
can encrypt the data before it leaves my
client machine so that the only thing
it's a restored here's
to data and you know when I read it back
I'll be back encrypted data and then
decrypt it locally on my own machine so
Kent storage service never sees private
data in the clear anyway so those are
all be sort of you know tantalizing
possibilities why you might like why
users might like this architecture all
right so you you know the if you dig
down to the nitty-gritty of what these
applications actually have to do they
you know you would need to work out a
whole lot of details like there needs to
be you know if my application is going
to be looking at your data there need to
be sort of conventions for how data
store here for example you know if I'm
gonna look at your recent posts you made
for our social networking application
you have to have stored them in your
storage under a key or a name that my
application knows to try to look look
for and you have to use a format that we
all understand so you know there's some
if we want to do sharing there's some
kind of standardization obstacles that
have to be overcome that don't really
exist for big websites because they can
just store their data however they like
okay so there's a question does this
adversely affect application performance
absolutely this is likely to be pretty
bad for performance because in the old
scheme the old scheme can be the
existing scheme can be implemented with
very high performance you know these
most of the web server may be making
hundreds of requests the database like
when you look at an Amazon web page for
example boy are there hundreds or
thousands of pieces of information that
had to be pulled out of Amazon's
databases you know when they're all in
the same machine room and those fetters
from the database take dozens of
microseconds but if one of these
applications needs to reach across the
internet you know maybe hundreds of
miles away to some storage service you
know it's now everything's going to take
ten or a hundred times as long to fetch
individual piece of data so now that's
certainly an issue and
you know it's the kind of that kind of
issue is the kind of thing that clever
designers can find ways to deal with so
it would certainly be a problem but my
guess is on the sort of total list of
reasons why this architecture is not
going to work there's a number of other
sort of equally unhappy puzzles and
although it would absolutely change how
people write applications because
instead of writing applications that
assemble lots of they use lots and lots
of pieces of data you would have to mean
much more parsimonious I think people
could work around it all right all right
so any any questions about this this
overall arrangement which is the sort of
arrangement that block stack is shooting
for so we should just sort of try to
guess even at this level what kind of
things might go wrong one reason is that
this interface is likely to be less
flexible than database interfaces and
this actually goes back to the
performance a little bit you know
weren't probably not going to be well I
mean this is sort of subject to design
but we're unlikely deals to be
supporting super flexible like sequel
queries and certainly it's unlikely that
we're going to be doing sequel queries
across other people's data as well as
ours for shared data so that's certainly
one potential problem is that this
interface may not be very expressive and
that's going to be painful for
programmers another question is could
this give users an amount of traffic
they might not handle yeah so that's
also a potential problem is that you
know if you don't have very powerful
queries much of what sequel is doing
when you talk to a real sequel database
is that it may be looking through cause
the database server to look through a
lot of data but it just finds the one
answer you're looking for maybe the sum
of all votes or something it just sends
that one little piece of final data back
whereas if you don't have a powerful
query language you may
up having to fetch a lot of stuff and
sort of do the filtering or aggregating
yourself and that just might be a lot of
data to be sending across peoples links
yeah so things might be slower things
would be slower and it's a question
whether they'd be too slow maybe in the
future in which you know everybody has
broadband internet and we have 5g cell
phones and none of this one it's
performance stuff will matter or maybe
it'll be important I don't know another
problem with this setup is that there
are some websites like eBay where it's
really not the case that all the data is
sort of definitely owned by one user so
for eBay for example well I have to have
two points here one is some data is not
owned by all users think about the front
page of Reddit right there's you know
there's some clever algorithms that
reddit is running to pick the order of
items in the front page I mean to do
with votes and you know who knows what
like weird those algorithms run and
where do they get the data and maybe
where do they store their conclusions
about the front page so that's something
it doesn't really fit in me you know
maybe you could be fit in here but I'd
be a little bit hard another kind of
website that seems like could be hard
here is is a Bay where you want to bid
against other people you know eBay tells
you whether you're have the current
highest bid which requires eBay to look
at other people's bids and then when you
finally win you know the amount you pay
has to do with the second highest bid
but those bids are private right you
don't want other people to see your bids
because then they can just bid one cent
higher than you and win at a low cost so
you know maybe you two user two is
stored a bid here but if my if I'm
bidding against user two and we need
this application to tell me if I'm the
winning bidder that means this
application needs in order to answer
that question may need probably needs to
know user to bid user twos bid which
means the users to bid has to be
accessible to me but if my application
code knows it well it's running on Mike
computer and I can change it right as
the usual rules for code you run in your
own computer and if I change my
application code to actually reveal your
bid then that's totally cheating from
the point of view of what eBay is trying
to do and so nobody would trust auction
system that allowed that so it's really
unclear you know there's probably tricks
that could be used but you know if we
just use this architecture and
straightforward way websites like eBay
that need to look at other people's
secret data but not review of the data
are quite a puzzle as just like and I
already mentioned that websites that
have to keep their own data like indexes
or vote counts or something that's often
a puzzle also a puzzle because there's
no notion here of you know the website
itself
there's just application code and
generic user owned storage because
usually these things so you would
probably have to augment this with some
crusted servers to run the privacy
critical part of eBay or whatever it
doesn't really fit into the model that
well another thing that's I'm gonna turn
out to be bad news here is that if I if
I have data that I want to share with
some people than others like I want to
share data with just six eight to four
students but not outsiders you know how
is that actually enforced
you know we'd really like to use end and
encryption so we don't have to trust the
storage server because after all that
was a big motivation for moving away
from the current website architectures
we don't want to have to trust these
sort of these clouds services so I could
encrypt the data so that 682 four
students could read it but it's actually
quite difficult to do that in any kind
of straightforward way you know I could
encrypt the data a hundred times you
know with once with each of the
sixty-two for students keys or maybe I
can encrypt the data once with uh some
sort of unique key and then encrypt that
key with a two for students keys or
something but then you run into a
question so if somebody drops the course
and you don't want them to be able to
see the data you know how do you make
sure that now they can't see the data so
you can use encryption for privacy but
once you get into a sort of complex
multi user applications with groups of
users for example cryptography becomes
can be quite difficult to use to solve
your privacy problems okay so these are
ways in which the system may be awkward
to awkward to program and because it may
be awkward to program and awkward to
program up features that may leak
through into the set of application
features you can have being limited also
which it's not going to make users very
happy either all right this is sort of a
high-level view of what block stack is
kind of working towards so now let's
that's may be focused a little more on
block stacks specifically where block
stack actually originated as a project
was as a secure naming scheme and you
can still see the the paper we read
today has a lot of preoccupation with
naming although if you look at their
current website and the current stuff
they write it's much more about this
decentralized architecture and
applications and much less about naming
but name is still very important for
them so the question is what are they
you know why are they interested in
names and what do they need from a
naming system so the kind of names
they're talking about in the paper and
then block stack in general are user
names these are really human users so
we're talking about names like you know
maybe Robert Morris right that's the
kind of name they're talking about
because you know in there in there are
decentralized architecture they don't
you know those kind of players in the
game or the users the users of the data
the users need to control who can see
their data so they need to be able to
name other users the specific things
they need to solve with naming they need
to if I
want to look at your data um block stack
needs to find where your data is you
know you're storing your data on some
storage server somewhere I need to know
what you know are using Amazon AWS or
maybe Microsoft Azure you know and if so
which server that Microsoft are
destroying your data so block stack
needs a way to map names to the location
where you store your data so that's one
big thing that they're doing with names
but they also need to find out if I
going to read your data I need to be
able to do things like check that it's
really your data you know I can't store
not the whole point of this is to not
have to trust the storage services so in
order for me to be able to check it that
it's your data we need a way to map the
name to the public key and we're gonna
assume that when you store data you sign
it with your public key first so we need
both DeMayo names to where to find the
person's data and map names the public
key that we used to check that when we
retrieve data it's really data that you
wrote and not some kind of misleading
thing cooked up by the storage service
or someone else
now this named a public key thing
actually is used in other ways too if I
want to encrypt data so that only you
can read it probably the way I'm gonna
do that is to encrypt the data or some
other key using your public key so that
only your private key can read it so if
I want to implement cryptographic ACLs
or really almost any permissions key
access control scheme I need you have I
need to build the name the people who
can use the data and so if I'm gonna
make access control lists these are
usually one way or another
driven by names and may be able to name
the people who can read my data so
this in particular this part that maps
names of people to public keys this is
usually often called a public key
infrastructure or PKI and so what block
sac is proposing among other things is a
general-purpose sort of public global
PKI public key infrastructure to map
user names to users public keys and this
is actually quite important because
people known for a long time decades
decades that in order to sort of make
big advances in Internet security almost
certainly the only way to do that is to
have some sort of public key scheme so
that people can sign you know data that
they produce email and check signatures
on email or data that they receive for
other people and also encrypt so that to
ensure privacy said on the intended
reader can be the data so almost any
internet wide scheme or large scheme
intended to get cryptographic privacy or
cryptographic authentication ends up
having to involve some sort of public
key system public key infrastructure so
that I can find out now given the
identity the person I want to talk to
how do I find their public key and yet
there kind of isn't a successful public
key infrastructure system out there
nobody's really figured out how to build
one of these that's actually useful and
as a result people have tended not to
build or deploy people tended not to
deploy
systems with cryptographic privacy and
authenticity because there's no PKI and
maybe because of that people haven't
worked on PGI's because it's not clear
who would use them but at any rate one
of the reasons why block stack is
interesting is because they're trying
hard to build a global scale public key
infrastructure
the kind of names remember the paper
talks about this Zuko's triangle thing
the kinds of names the style of names
that the paper's talking about is three
these three interesting properties one
is their unique and what that really
means actually is that the names have
global meaning that the name Robert for
example has the same meaning did it
everyone in the world you know maps to
this in the same way the same data
location same public key to everyone in
the world of course that's a little
ridiculous for Robert you know
presumably my ID under block stack would
be much longer than that you know maybe
Robert Morris there's a lot of Robert
Morris's maybe I'm Robert Morris number
67 is Robert Morris to register with
block stack that would probably be
closer to what my name would be under
block stack anyway that everybody in the
world when they see this name and they
run it through the PKI gets the same
information about it so this really
means global might be a better word for
this the second property the paper talks
about for names are there human readable
just like Robert Morris so somebody
could look at it and you know make a
guess what a name means and maybe people
may be able to remember the names
because they sort of have human
meaningfulness and the final thing
they're interested in is that the naming
system the allocation of names be
decentralized and you know the paper
claims on this is the old claim that
it's difficult to get all three you know
apparently not impossible since the
paper does it the sort of intuitive
reason why it's hard to get all three is
that if you have a supposing you have
assistants decentralized there's no one
entity you know in charge of allocating
names well if you do that then it's very
hard to ensure uniqueness that is if you
don't have some single entity handing
out the names how do you know you don't
end up handing out the name same name
the multiple people if there's not some
central trusted entity and you can
actually have decentralized and unique
names
but now the most obvious ways to do that
sacrifice the human readable part so if
what you decide your names are are gonna
be you know public keys 1000 bit public
keys in a public private cryptography
system anybody can make up a new
public/private key pair they're
typically made use random number and
emmm number generator so since anyone
can make one up and they're generated
randomly they're going to be unique but
they're not human readable so you know
many of the obvious ways trying to get
all three of these at the same time
don't work so well the way block stack
solves these this at a very high level I
mean you know they're gonna produce
their decentralized system and no
central person handing out names the
names are human readable and everyone
sees the same set of mappings the way
they do this at a high level is that
they rely on bitcoins ability to produce
a single ordered log of transactions
that's one way of viewing Bitcoin is
that everybody agrees on what the
sequence of Bitcoin blocks is and you
know maybe you get temporary Forks but
Bitcoin rapidly resolves any Forks and
causes everyone to agree on what the
sequence of blocks is in Bitcoin ok so
once we a Bitcoin that's causing
agreement on a sequence of transactions
we can stick anyone can stick
transactions into the Bitcoin log that
you know as well as maybe being valid
Bitcoin transactions also have hidden
away in them name reservation records so
now this is it's a sort of naming on
Bitcoin
you
blockchain so you know Bitcoin was
already put getting us sort of unique
and globally agreed sequence of these
transaction blocks and now and anybody
can submit a transaction so in that
sense it's totally decentralized right
so how wouldn't what the way block stack
uses this for naming is that if I want
to register a name I can pick any name I
like say Robert Morris as long as it's
not already you in use and I stick in I
submit to Bitcoin a transaction you know
that happens to be a valid Bitcoin
transaction but it's also going to be
meaningful to block stack and it's gonna
say please reserve please allocate the
name RTM and map it to whatever my
public key and my information about
where to have data not man anyone can
submit these and the block stack servers
all the blocks tax servers watch the
Bitcoin blockchain as it involves and
every time they see one of these records
that's a block stack transaction as well
as a Bitcoin transaction the block stack
servers think about adding this mapping
to their name database but they have a
set of rules for rejecting bad block
stack transactions in the Bitcoin
blockchain so for example if some bad
person after I've allocated RTM
themselves try to allocate RTM well they
can submit any transaction they like so
they can perfectly well also submit a
transaction trying to steal the name RTM
from me and mapping it to some other
public key that they know the private
key for well all the block stack servers
are watching the Bitcoin chain there's
only one Bitcoin chain and only has a
one set of contents and so the block
stack servers as they you know sort of
look at successive transactions in the
Bitcoin chain are gonna see my
allocation first and then they're gonna
see this other person's allocation for
the same name and the rules going to be
well of a name is already Alec
you can't be allocated a second time and
the block stack servers will ignore this
attempted registration of a name so
what's being implemented here is a kind
of first-come first-serve scheme for
allocating names the first person to get
a allocation record into the blockchain
wins that name okay so as far as those
three properties the Zucco triangle
properties it's decentralized because
you know we can uh we believe that
bitcoin is be decentralized and there's
no sort of other entity deciding who
gets what's name it's really just this
first-come first-served scheme that was
decentralized the names can be anything
there's no any strings whatever so
they're perfectly reasonable to put
human readable names in here and
everybody's looking at the same
blockchain for any name they all see
they all agree on what the first
registration of that name is so it's
unique or globally meaningful as well so
block sac has managed to actually get
all three of these Zucco properties in
their naming system there's a question
does this mean that the block stack
servers have to scan the entire chain
from back to front for adding new names
yeah so in principle sure the state of
the name database is really the result
of interpreting the whole blockchain but
of course you know the block stack
servers will will cash you know cash the
latest state they've seen and as these
in a database so each block stacks are
you know maybe he's read this far and
Bitcoin blockchain and has a database
that has the current mapping for every
name seen in all the box before this and
when they see a new block from Bitcoin
they'll just look at the transactions
and update their database incrementally
to reflect these transactions so getting
a new block stack server up to speed
actually does take quite a long time and
I think when some paper I read said it
might take up to a couple of days um but
once your block stack server is up to
speed then it's all sort of incremental
additions after that
but you know there's the larger point is
that it is indeed the case that block
stack is kind of piggybacking on Bitcoin
and you know you could easily argue that
bitcoin is not very scalable ultimately
or uses that too much electric power who
knows what too slow takes a long time to
reflect new transactions and the cities
are all sort of somewhat undesirable
properties that block stack is
inheriting from Bitcoin but nevertheless
you know it's not there's not aware of
another way of getting all three of
those Zuko's properties in a naming
system so if you value them your options
are not you know a lot of options other
than this approach okay so we may ask
ourselves whether this naming scheme
this way of mapping names to public keys
and places to find the data whether it's
whether it really has properties that we
actually like so let's go back over
those three properties so one the the
the names are unique everybody in this
system agrees on what our TM means it's
really that the names of global meaning
so question is whether whether we care
about this whether this is a good
property so one you know one thing on
the plus side for this is that it makes
that having these names like this human
you know if that having globally
relevant names means that we can talk
about names with each other I can email
you a name and that name will have the
same meaning for you as it does for me
because we're both gonna look it up in
the blockchain and get the same result
and so that's nice it also means that I
can look at names that are recorded
somewhere like in an access control list
and kind of understand know what they're
going to me
but some things that are maybe not so
great about this is that if you have to
choose your names from a single global
pool because that's what we're doing
here right the since there's just one
naming system there's just one set of
names it's gonna mean that it'll be
actually hard to look at a name and
decide if it's the name you want like my
name would actually probably be as I
mentioned before you know maybe you know
our TM nine five five eight seven
depending on how many our teams are so
this may be my name it's actually very
hard to look at that and decide is that
the RTM that you really met and so that
really undermines the human readable
property that they have here
the bigger the system is the kind of
less valuable having human readable
names is just people at MIT and maybe
maybe there's only one Robert Morris at
MIT although actually there's more than
one but in other across the world the
kind of justification for caring about
what their names are human readable
that's I guess is very slim it's also a
human readable can be deceptive
depending on what's going on so if you
see a name that looks like you know RTM
at MIT that edu if you see that name and
block stack or something it's tempting
to imagine that it might be connected to
that email address all right because it
looks as human readable it like looks
like it has meaning that's the whole
point of having human readable names is
that they kind of suggest meaning to
people these four blocks stack that's
deeply misleading a block stack the
names really don't mean anything it
simply first-come first-serve so all we
know all we can tell by seeing this name
our team at MIT de ed you from block
stack is that this is this name means
the first person this name refers to the
first person who registered this name
that's all we know initially it might be
me might be somebody else there's no
reason to believe it's me or that it's
associated with MIT or anything else all
we know is that this name is owned by
whoever registered at first now if I
establish say secure email conversation
with whoever owns this name you know
using the key that flops that map's us
to and I spend some time talking to them
you know maybe I can eventually
convinced myself that they're the person
who I think they are but the name alone
is looks like it's meaningful but
probably is not in fact very meaningful
so that's a real defect in human
readable names it could be defective and
you know related
the block SEC naming scheme doesn't help
me find if if I sort of know who I want
to talk to block sacks not really
helping me will fiying the name of the
person I want to talk to you know I mean
maybe you know you want to send email to
Robert Morris you know gosh this is
deeply unhelpful and it's the only thing
in the block stack naming system these
names that are like this so it's really
not necessarily solving the problem
people have which is I know I sort of
know in my head who I want to talk to
but I don't know their public key and I
don't know their block stack name either
how do I find their blocks technique so
that's a sort of a defect in this system
you have to really have to already know
the name if you want to use blocks
naming scheme but how do you find those
names some other options that you could
consider for naming I'm in a system the
sort of larger decentralized system one
is that we could just abandon names
human readable names you know not try to
get all three of those Zucco properties
and just use public keys directly so
that would mean if I want to interact
with you I need to find your public keys
somehow maybe you just send it to me
maybe you tell me something over the
phone I can use to get your public key
maybe you send me a secure message or
write on us with the paper or something
so we could just use directly use public
keys and then we wouldn't have to solve
all these problems although of course
they're awkward but maybe I can store
the public keys I know about in my
personal contact list and they'll be
helpful be like telephone numbers of
telephone numbers don't mean anything
but once I know your phone number I can
stick it in my contact list another
possible approach would be to abandon
the decentralized part and just try to
cook up some central entity that would
actually reliably verify identity that
some centralized entity you know maybe
the Social Security system that hands
out Social Security numbers or you know
whoever it is that hands out driver's
license or something and kind of
piggyback on their work to establish a
centralized notion of you
any kind of verified names that's
actually remarkably difficult also but
you know it's another avenue to think
about anyway so block stack took this
particular approach to try to get names
all right um the let me just kind of
outline the big picture of the pieces in
block stack which is sort of a
refinement of the decentralized
application diagram that I showed before
sort of at the bottom they have this
Bitcoin system that's chugging along
with Bitcoin blocks and the carry along
kind of unknown to Bitcoin these blocks
tech transactions there's a bunch of
block stack naming system servers and
it's not really clear whether they
intend ordinary people to run them or
that they would be a service in a way it
makes the most sense for ordinary people
to run them on their own laptops because
you have to trust them but that may not
be so great anyway these blocks like
naming service servers read the
blockchain and kind of accumulate a
database these at least in the first
instance what's in block what's in the
Bitcoin blockchain is public keys and
the hash the cryptographic hash of
information describing where each user
stores their data because you could
store that information this is just you
know Artyom stores is data in Amazon AWS
or something but that's too big to sort
of conveniently store Bitcoin and so
there's this kind of intermediate layer
called Atlas it was really it's only job
is to map hashes of information that are
stashed and Bitcoin into these own
information
one's own record per user and so that
means that my you know if I have an RT M
registration and box tack that holds
with a hash my zone record this just has
the name or the you know Internet
address or something of where I store my
data so it might be you know AWS slash
know whatever identifier I used to
uniquely identify the stuff that I store
in AWS and this is really a reference to
my where my storage sits where all my
key value pairs are stored now the paper
I think the papers vision is that you be
able to have your zone record point to
any cloud storage out there
in fact the cloud storage system has to
you know obey the block stack interface
and so you can't just use in the
existing cloud storage system so in
practice these all point to block at the
moment of these blocks tax on gaia
servers they run this and these are just
storage servers that know about
different block stack users and store
their key value pairs for them and that
means if i want to read your data out of
if i'm running in a block second
application that wants to read your data
i need to apply your name somehow i
gotta find your name maybe you tell me
your name over the phone i type your
name into the application i'm using
maybe it's a to do this manager and used
to go out and find your to do list items
to show me my app is gonna contact a
block stack naming system server and ask
it to translate your name it's been
watching the blockchain it keeps a
mapping it knows how to use the hash to
find your zone record your zone record
points to some data owned by you and
Gaia and then my app fetches this data
it needs to verify the data so all
blocks active apps expect data to be
signed by the owner in Gaia and the
public key to check your signature on
the data you know I can use your public
key or public keys embedded and
your record and Bitcoin and so I can use
it to my app really can use it to check
the signature here make sure that this
is data that you actually produced and
not something that an untrustworthy gaya
server okay so that's sort of a basic
outline of how this works it it turns
out that sort of embedding their
information on the Bitcoin blockchain is
not as straightforward as I described
they they have they need to take special
efforts to detect Forks for example
because they don't get to the blocks
that name servers don't sort of get to
realize directly that there's been a
fork that to detect it I mean they means
the detective cuz the fork might be part
of an attack and you know the Bitcoin
isn't filtering out bad records for them
and so they have to do their own and
force their own rules on the records
they get out like ignoring duplicate
registrations there's they also turns
out need to chart they charge fees for
registering a name and that means that
the Bitcoin transaction that is the
registration of a name has to pay some
money to what's called a burn address
pay some Bitcoin current bitcoins to a
burn address in order to have the right
to register that name and the block
stack name service actually checked at
each name registration transaction did
pay enough Bitcoin to this burn address
for which there's no private key so that
money simply disappears and the reason
they do this the reason why they require
every name registration to waste some
money is that otherwise it's too easy
for bad people to just register lots and
lots of names like certainly the
experience with the domain naming system
where for a while name registration was
free those that people who just register
you know every single you know one two
and three letter combination that's
possible and they wouldn't own all these
names for free or somebody knowing that
I would really like to own the name RTM
might register before me
and then if I wanted to use it I have to
pay them so in order to try to deter
that they have a they require fees and
that's actually pulmo probably an
important part of of the design since
free stuff on the internet tends to be
yeah
tends to be abused or sort of drowned
out in intentional spam all right one
detail on this picture so I left out the
claw in this picture we have the client
machines running some app this is the
client device now when the app needs to
get out my data get at my data it needs
to be able to decrypt it whenever it
writes data into my guys storage my app
needs to be able to encrypt it
ultimately using my private key and when
I fetch data back it nice to be able to
decrypt it also ultimately one way or
another using my private key so these
applications need to get at private keys
but private keys are super duper
sensitive and whereas these apps are
just whatever junk I downloaded from the
block stack app store and possibly
totally untrustworthy so we never want
to give them a private key so what
actually happens is that there's a
separate program that I'm always running
called the block stack browser and it's
this program
that knows my private key and so if the
app wants to do stuff as me is really
got to first do it through the block
stack browser and in fact the way this
place has so complicated in detail the
block style browser essentially makes up
kind of per app private key in this app
uses just the per app private key and
not my real sort of master private key
so this app again doesn't get to know my
real private key but this issue of not
revealing sensitive key material to the
these apps which may be indeed quite
untrustworthy as an important detail and
blocks that keeps my master private key
secret now on the topic of private keys
a weakness in essentially every system
you know like Bitcoin itself and block
stack and also is that users tend not to
be as careful as they ought to be about
private keys so am i you know if I'm
gonna use block stack from my phone you
know that means my phone has to know my
private key if I leave my phone in the
cafeteria
then whoever finds it now has a device
that has my private key in it and can do
anything as me because as far as block
attack is concerned they are me they
know my private key users also tend to
lose private keys you know I don't use
the service for a little while you know
I forget whatever passphrase it was for
example that was protecting the private
key or I put my private key on a USB
someone key from somewhere for
safekeeping and then lose the USB key so
that's completely routine problem that
users have and block attack actually
does not really have an answer to these
questions I'm a pretty much assume the
users will be careful of their private
keys and if you lose your private key
blocks that can't get it back for you
it's like it's in order to be super
secure in order if you're not to have to
trust block stack only your client knows
your private key if you lose your client
we forget your what are the
phrases you're just completely out of
luck and blocks that can't help you and
so this is just a difficulty in real
life people don't want to use systems
that are that brittle and in real life
what ends up happening is that even
systems that have you know serious
cryptography usually have some sort of
key retrieval scheme whereby I can stir
something I can tell a block stack maybe
my mother's maiden name or you know they
send me an SMS thing to my telephone or
whatever some scheme I can use to
recover my private key and those if you
want to attack a system it's often the
password recovery of the key recovery
aspect of the system that's the easiest
to attack I just call a block stack I
said I said tell them you know I'm
really I'm Robert Morris you got to
believe me please you know we said
Robert Morris it's key for me your
password
nah man tell me the new password and if
I'm convincing enough you know and the
system allows sets they're gonna
let me have it and they're probably also
presumably if it's an attacker really
who is calling and pretending to be me
they'll let the attacker reset the
password of the key or whatever blocks
that happens not to allow that because
it's so obviously insecure but real
world systems if they don't want their
users to abandon them need to have a
better plan and it's not clear how to
make that better all right
all right there's a couple of sort of
issues I want to talk about that come up
in the system for me the block stack is
really a kind of source of questions to
think about or even kind of things that
are not really well you know suggestions
for use for more things to work on you
know block SEC I think black sex
situation now is that you probably
wouldn't actually want to use it to
build a real system for real users but
it's kind of trying to point the way to
a system that might someday be if enough
cleverness was put into it enough
development was done on it might
actually be a system that was both
convenient for programmers and actually
provided some real value for users but
probably not there yet but its entrance
to think about you know how it could be
designed differently or better in order
to kind of get it closer to something
that were really useful so one question
you might have especially in the context
of a to for is whether block stack
really needs to use Bitcoin like that
points really not you know not that
great the fees that you have to pay you
know to register a name you know vary in
value in Bitcoin by factors of you know
100 almost every night overnight at
times in addition people really down the
way like the way Bitcoin you uses
proof-of-work to burn up CPU in order to
be secure so you know Bitcoin is not
perfect although it's kind of an
important part of the system otherwise
they couldn't you know they it's not
clear how they would do names without
this whole Bitcoin tie-in and so one
question you might have eight to four is
whether I'm certificate transparency
which is a you know we looked at it last
week a certificate transparency does not
have mining does not have proof of work
and yet you know it's powerful enough to
be helpful in a naming system and so
question is whether said of Bitcoin
whether box that could use something
like certificate transparency not in
order to
enforce adequate rules about names and
actually don't know the answer to that
my guess is the answer's no my feeling
is that while certificate transparency
can reveal conflicts or conflicts really
is a to people registering the same name
like if you required everybody to submit
their name registrations to a
certificate transparency log yes indeed
you would be able to see that two people
had registered the same name but
certificate transparency doesn't resolve
ownership conflicts so if I register RT
you know supposedly last year I
registered RT M and I've been using it
happily for the next year and then
somebody else registers RT M today yeah
you know they'll submit their
registration to a certificate
transparency log and so now maybe that
will make my name unusable or something
but it's not clear really who should own
the name because certificate
transparency doesn't have very powerful
mechanisms for resolving these conflicts
you might think that order would be
enough but the same records and
different certificate transparency logs
can have different order because there's
nothing forcing the different
transparency logs to to have exactly the
same order and if you want you know how
come Bitcoin can enforce every replica
of the blocks you'd add the same order I
believe the answer to that really boils
down to bitcoins mining bitcoins mining
that resolves Forks it resolves
deferring copies the blockchain and
forces agreement and if you don't do
mining at least you know or something
like mining it's it's not that clear how
to add a enforce agreement on the order
of the records so in addition the fees
the block stack charges are probably
critical to avoid various kinds of spam
in the naming system various kinds of
abuse and you know block stack built on
Bitcoin can sort of automatically
require people to pay to register block
stack built on certificate transparency
you know
there's no direct mechanism to require
fees and in fact that I think the point
here is actually quite a bit larger and
that's that a lot of people talk about
using blockchains for lots of stuff
other than cryptocurrency but in fact it
seems difficult to use blockchains open
block chains with unrestricted access
except when they're coupled with some
kind of crypto car
cryptocurrency again I don't know if
that's true but it's certainly my
impression all right so a big question
with block stack is whether it's going
to be convenient for programmers and to
me the this questions absolutely
critical because it's one of two very
critical questions the other one is the
other critical question is whether it
makes users lives better the my
perception at the moment is that indeed
box AK is not particularly convenient
for programmers I think I've used block
stack a program block stack I've tried
to build system to like it and my strong
impression is that it's just a lot more
difficult to build a web application on
one of these decentralized platforms
than it is on the ordinary platform and
you know that's kind of damaging because
if the website developers aren't on
board then nobody's gonna get a lot of
traction and if the website developers
don't like you know I sort of feel that
the system is difficult to program the
only way that you're ever gonna get any
traction is if the attraction to users
is so strong that it that you know users
demand decentralized applications and
that might force programmers to use it
but the programmers just speaking for
themselves my guess is that the
architecture in which basically all the
code is sitting in the client and we
don't have special you know website
servers is just pretty painful it's hard
to have data that's specific to the
application because all data is owned by
users it's hard to have indices or you
know counts of likes or vote
you know the kind of front page rankings
as I mentioned for reddit or hacker news
are difficult there's all kinds of stuff
it's a pain if you don't have a notion a
notion of the website itself with its
own data this the access control is
actually equally painful it's very easy
to write the code and a traditional
website to decide who gets to see what
data in a decentralized system and
really you only can be enforced using
cryptographic access control or these
that's the way it seems from the example
a block stack and it just turns out for
all except for very straightforward like
one user using their own private data
using cryptography to enforce access
well it's just pretty painful
so programmers might only be excited if
users were excited so our users gonna be
excited you know one way to look at that
one way to ask that question is whether
this kind of decentralized use your own
storage is good for user privacy because
that's one of the big pitches is that by
storing data on storage services the
users own and pay for you know maybe
that'll keep the data more private more
secure than storing their data on
websites so that really am I asking is a
better than trusting Facebook or Google
to keep my data private both from
Facebook employees and from other users
of the site and from hackers you might
try to break in and that's just a
question right you know sort of depends
on how much you trust Facebook the fact
is that you're still storing your data
out there in the cloud on some service
just maybe not Facebook and you're still
running software on your client that is
presumably provided to you by Facebook
so you're running Facebook software and
your client you know it's so you're
still kind of trusting this this this
code that facebook gives you or wherever
you get your code from and you know for
the real hackers among us you can look
at the code and convince yourself
because you're running it on your own
computer and can meet yourself
okay but for the general public you know
the difference between talking to
Facebook's web software on their web
server and my name's Facebook software
and their own client may not seem very
great and who knows maybe the Facebook
app you're running is sort of sending
Facebook information about what you're
up to snooping on you there's a question
about wise cryptographic access control
painful for programmers um one way of
looking at it is that the access control
checks that you have to do in a sort of
standard web site are very
straightforward you just write a little
bit of Python code or whatever it is to
decide whether some user should be able
to see some data and you can even
compute using data that the user
shouldn't see as long as you don't
reveal it to the user
whereas in anything but simple
situations doing the cryptography to
allow some users but not others to get
out your data it just requires a lot
more thought so you know suppose the MIT
registrar maintains a list of all the
people taking 8 to 4 and if so as a
group so they maintain that list and I
want to use it in order to govern the
protections for some file stored in
Krypton with cryptographic protection
and block stack because that lists that
group list of eight to four students may
change you know the what I do for
encryption may have to change too so I
you know if I encrypt I could encrypt
the data once with the key of each user
in the a to four group list and that
would work because they could just read
the copy that was encrypted for them but
then as users are added that the
Registrar changes the list as or deletes
users
I need my software I needs to notice
that that list has changed and busily go
out and change the way stuff is
encrypted we encrypt for the new users
deleting two copies for the old users
and that's just like a level of damage
that or a level of kind of complexity
that doesn't exist in current systems
not necessarily they can't be done
but it just does require a lot of
machinery that is not ordinarily needed
all right another sort of trust issue
from the point of view of users is that
they still have to trust their storage
provider to preserve their data and they
still have just trust their storage
provider to always serve up the most
recent copy right the cheating storage
provider might try to cause trouble by
serving up an old version so we lease in
that block stack design you know you're
really trusting your storage server this
central service is from your point of
view to do the right thing with your
data to preserve it to back it up to
produce it when asked for to produce the
right version when asked for and it is a
bit of a question for just ordinary
people that if you're trusting Amazon
AWS to store your data correctly and not
lose it it's not that much bigger of a
step to trust Amazon itself to run the
website and you know we can argue about
with it that's really exactly true but I
think you know from a high-level point
of view from most people most ordinary
people it's really a pretty pretty small
distinction and you would have to
overcome that in order to persuade
people that boy you know the block stack
approach of using Amazon as a storage
service is better than the standard way
of using Amazon as a website another
question from users point of view
another pitch for why that decentralized
architecture might be better for users
is that it gives them more control over
over you know not privacy but just sort
of what applications they use with their
data so if you want to switch
applications but still use the same data
like change photo editing apps like I
mentioned in principle that should be
easier with this sort of decentralized
app architecture because the you know
the again the data is not owned by the
application website if you want to use
the same data in multiple different
applications like I want to
a calendar app but use the same data
from my email app that also is you know
relatively convenient with the
decentralized scheme because the data is
sort of again independent from the
applications you know maybe users want
this maybe they don't probably not at
the top of anybody's list and there's an
additional problem that in order even
for that vision to work there has to be
a lot of standardization of formats of
files so you know the calendar file my
calendar program has to store its
calendar data in a format that my email
program can understand otherwise that
doesn't work and if I'm gonna switch
email applications well my old email
application better have been storing my
email in a format that my new email
application can understand otherwise
this vision of decentralized apps me
easy to switch among can't be made to
come true a final issue that worries me
about this whole thing is that it's not
clear that users are going to be willing
to pay for their own storage if people
aren't willing to pay for that I'm
storage then this whole arrangement is
pretty unattractive because a lot of the
point was to sort of give the users more
responsibility over their own storing
their own stuff users of I think or so
used free advertise advertisements
supported services that they just might
not be willing to get on board with with
paying for internet stuff
alright nevertheless I feel like this
whole area is you know well worth
keeping an eye on maybe even worth sort
of working on different pieces of it to
be are interested in looking for
research problems and well I don't
really believe it right now for the
reasons that I outlined I think it's
absolutely worth pursuing because
someday if like definitely the way this
these kinds of decentralized systems
work has been getting better and may
eventually be good enough that that
there's serious competition for
existing website architectures and I
would just love it if if such serious
competition like that were to arise all
right
that's all I have to say next Tuesday
the last class amazing meeting is going
to be project presentation so I'll get
to hear what what everybody who hasn't
been doing lab four has been up to
please ask me questions if you have