um maybe maybe we should get started um
it's been a long time since we've all
been in the same place at night I hope
everybody's doing well today I'd like to
talk about spanner the reason to talk
about this paper is that it's a rare
example of a system provides distributed
transactions over data that's widely
separated that is data that might be
scattered all over the internet and
different data centers I'm Saul most
never done in production systems of
course it's extremely desirable to be
able to have transactions the
programmers really like it and also
extremely desirable to have data spread
all over the network for both for fault
tolerance and to ensure that data is
near that there's a copy of the data
near everybody who wants to use it and
on the way to achieving this spanner
used at least two neat ideas one is that
they run two-phase commit but they
actually run it over paxos replicated
participants I'm in order to avoid the
problem the two-phase commit that a
crashed coordinator can block everyone
and the other interesting idea is that
they use synchronize time in order to
have very efficient read-only
transactions and the system is is that
actually been very successful it's used
a lot by many many different services
inside of Google it's been turned by
Google into a product to service for
their cloud-based customers and it's
inspired a bunch of other research and
other systems both sort of by the
example that it's kind of wide area
transactions are possible and also
specifically there's at least one opens
her system cockroach DB that uses a lot
of explicitly uses a lot of the design
the motivating use case the reason that
the paper says they first kind of
started the design spanner was that they
were already had a actually they had
many big database systems and
Google but their advertising system in
particular the data was shorted over
many many distinct my sequel and
BigTable databases and maintaining that
sharding was a just an awkward and
manual and time-consuming process in
addition their previous advertising
database system didn't allow
transactions that spanned more than a
single basically more than a single
server but they really wanted to be able
to have to spread their data out more
widely for better performance and to
have transactions over the multiple
shards of the data for their advertising
database apparently the workload was
dominated by read-only transactions I
mean you can see this in table 6 where
the there's billions of read-only
transactions and only millions of
readwrite transactions so they're very
interested in the performance of
read-only of transactions that only do
weeds and apparently they also required
strong consistency and that you know
what transactions in particular so they
wanted serializable transactions and
they also wanted external consistency
which means that if one transaction
commits and then after it finishes
committing another transaction starts
the second transaction needs to see any
modification is done by the first and
this external consistency turns out to
be interesting with replicated data all
right so
ownage are just a basic arrangement sort
of physical arrangement of their servers
that that spanner uses it has the its
servers are spread over data centers
presumably all over the world certainly
all over the United States and each
piece of data is replicated at multiple
data centers so the diagrams got to have
multiple data centers let's say there's
there's three data centers really
there'd be many more oops
so we have all day
dissenters then the data shard it that
it's broken up you can think of it has
been being broken up by key into and
split over many servers so maybe there's
one server that serves keys starting
with a in this data center or another
starting with B and so forth lots of
lots of charting with lots of servers in
fact every data center has on any piece
of data is any shard is replicated at
more than one data center so there's
going to be another copy another replica
of the a keys and the B keys and so on
the second day in the center and yet
another hopefully identical copy of all
this data at the third data center in
addition each data center has multiple
clients or their clients of spanner and
what these clients really are as web
servers so if our ordinary human beings
sitting in front of a web browser
connects to some Google service that
uses spanner
they'll connect to some web server in
one of the data centers and that's going
to be one of these one of these spanner
clients all right so that is replicated
the replication is managed by Paxos in
fact that really a variant of Paxos that
has leaders and is really very much like
the raft that we're all familiar with
and each Paxos instance manages all the
replicas of a given shard of the data so
this shard all the copies of this shard
form one Paxos group and all the
replicas are this shard form other packs
was group and within each these are
these patches instances independent as
its own leader runs its own version of
the of the poem instance of the packs
was protocol numb and the reason for the
sharding and for the independent paxos
instances per shard is to allow parallel
speed-up and a lot of parallel
throughput because there's a vast number
of clients you know which are
representing working on behalf of web
browsers so this huge number typically
of concurrent
requests and so it pays and more
immensely to split them up over multiple
shards and multiple sort of Paxos groups
that are running in parallel okay and
you can think of or each of these paxos
groups has a leader a lot like wrath so
maybe the leader for this shard isn't
data is a replica in datacenter one and
the leader for this shard might be the
replica and datacenter two and and so
forth and you know so that means that if
you need to if a client needs to do a
right it has to send that right to the
leader of the of the shard whose data it
needs to write just with Raph these
Paxos instances are what they're really
doing is sending out a log the leader is
sort of replicating a log of operations
to all the followers and the followers
execute that log which is for data is
gonna be reads and writes so it executes
those logs all in the same order all
right so the reason for these for this
setup the sharding as I mentioned for
throughput the multiple copies in
different data centers is for two
reasons one is you want copies and
different data centers in case one data
center fails if you know maybe you power
fails to the entire city the data
centers in or there's an earthquake or a
fire or something you'd like other
copies that other data centers that are
maybe not going to fail at the same time
and then you know there's a price to pay
for that because now the paxos protocol
now has to talk maybe over long
distances to talk to followers and
different data centers the other reason
to have data in multiple data centers is
that it may allow you to have copies of
the data near all the different clients
that use it so if you have a piece of
data that may be read in both California
and New York maybe it's nice to have a
copy of that data one copy in California
one copy in New York so that reads can
be very fast and indeed a lot of the
focus that
time is to make reads from the local the
nearest replica both fast and correct
finally another interesting interaction
between Paxos and multiple data centers
is that
paxos lie craft only requires a majority
in order to replicate a log entry and
proceed and that means if there's one
slow or distant or flaky data center the
Paxil system can keep chugging along and
accepting new requests even if one data
center is is being slow all right so
with this arrangement there's a couple
of big challenges that paper has to bite
off one is they really want to do reads
from local data centers but because
they're using Paxos and because Paxos
only requires each log entry to be
replicated on a majority that means a
minority of the replicas may be lagging
and may not have seen the latest data
that's been committed by paxos and that
means that if we allow clients to read
from the local replicas for speed they
may be reading out-of-date data if their
replica happens to be in the minority
that didn't see the latest updates so
they have to since they're requiring
correctness they're requiring this
external consistency idea that every
read see the most up-to-date data they
have to have some way of dealing with
the possibility that the local replicas
may be lagging another issue they have
to deal with is that a transaction may
involve multiple shards and therefore
multiple paxos groups so you may be
reading or writing a single transaction
may be reading or writing multiple
records in the database that are stored
in multiple shards and multiple Paxil
scripts so those have to be we need
distributed transactions okay so I'm
going to explain how the transactions
work that's going to be the kind of
focus of the lecture spanner actually
beats implements readwrite transactions
quite differently from read-only
transactions so let me start with your
beauty of readwrite transactions which
are so have a lot more conventional in
their design alright so first readwrite
transactions let me just remind you at a
transaction looks like so let's just
choose a simple one that's like
mimicking bank transfer so I'm one of
those client machines a client of
spanner you'd run some code you run this
transaction code the code would say oh
I'm beginning a transaction and then I
would say oh I want to read and write
these records so maybe you have a bank
balance in database record X and we want
to you know increment and increase this
bank balance and decrease y's bank
balance and oh that's the end of the
transaction and now the client hopes the
database will go off and commit that
alright so I want to trace through all
the steps that that have to happen in
order to in order for spanner to execute
this read write transaction so first of
all there's a client in one of the data
centers that's driving this transaction
so I'll draw this client here let's
imagine that x and y are on different
shards since that's the that's the
interesting case and that those shards
each of the two shards is replicated in
three different data centers so know we
got our three data centers here and at
each data center there's a server that
I'm just going to write x for the
replicas of the shard that's holding act
with the bank balance for x and y for
the these three servers spinner once
two-phase commit just to totally stand
our two-phase commit and two phase
locking almost exactly as described in
the reading from last week from the 603
three textbook and the huge difference
is that instead of the participants and
the transaction manager being individual
computers the participants in the
transaction manner manager are Paxos
replicated
groups of servers for increased fault
tolerance so that means just to remind
you that the shard the three replicas of
the shard that stores X it's a really
app access group same with these three
replicas strong Y and we'll just imagine
that for each of these one of the three
servers is the leader so let's say the
server and data center 2 is the Paxos
leader for the X is shard and the
servant is saying one is the Paxos
leader for y sharp okay so the first
thing that happens is that the coin
picks a unique transaction ID which is
going to be carried on all these
messages so that the system knows that
all the different operations are
associated with a single transaction the
first thing that does the client has to
be so despite the way the code looks
where it reads and writes X then read
some write Y in fact the way the code
has transaction code has to be organized
it has to do all its reads first and
then at the very end do all the writes
at the same time essentially as part of
the commit so the clients to do good
reads it turns out that it in order to
maintain locks since just as as in last
week's 6:53 reading every time you read
or write a data item the server
responsible for it has to associate a
lock with that data item the locks are
maintained the read locks and spanner
maintain only in the Paxos leader so
when the client transaction wants to
read access sends a read X request to
the leader of X is shard and that leader
of the shard returns the current value
of x plus sets a lock on X of course if
the locks already set then you won't
respond to the client until whatever
transaction currently has the data
locked releases the lock by committing
and then the leader for that shard since
back the value of x to client the client
needs to read Y got lucky this time
because the
assuming like clients in data center one
the leaders in the local data center so
this reads gonna be a lot faster that
reads sets the lock on Y in the taxes
leader and then returns okay's now the
clients on all the reads it does
internal computations and figures out
the writes that wants to do what values
wants to write to x and y and so now the
clients going to send out the updated
values for the records that it wants to
write and it does this all at once at
the end towards the end of the
transaction so the first thing it does
is it chooses one of the packs those
groups to act as the transaction
coordinator and as it chooses us in
advance and it's gonna send out the
identity of the which Paxos group is
going to act as the transaction
coordinator so let's assume it chooses
this Paxos group i've split a double box
here to say that not only is this server
the leader of its Paxos group it's also
acting as transaction coordinator for
this transaction then the client sends
out the updated values that it wants to
write so it's going to send a write
extra write X request here with a new
value and the identity of the
transaction coordinator when each the
Paxos leader for each written value
receives the write request it sends out
a prepare message to its followers and
gets that into the Paxos log so that
I'll represent that by P into the paxos
log because it's gonna commit to being
able to come it's the wrong word it's
promising to be able to carry out this
transaction that it hasn't crashed for
example and lost its locks so it sends
out this prepare message logs the
prepare message through paxos when it
gets a majority of responses from the
followers then this pacts was leader
sends a yes to the transaction
coordinator saying yes I am a promising
to be able to carry out my part of the
trend
right to Y V and notionally the
transaction see the client also
sentenced the value to be bitten - why -
why's paxos leader and this server
acting as paxos leader sends out prepare
messages to his followers and logs it
impacts those weights for the
acknowledgments from a majority and then
you can think of it as as the Paxos
leaders sending the transaction
coordinator which is on the same machine
maybe the same program a yes vote saying
yes I can I can commit okay so when the
transaction coordinator gets responses
from all the different from the leaders
of all the different shards whose data
is involved in this transaction if they
all said yes then the transaction
coordinator can commit otherwise it
can't let's assume it decides to commit
at that point the transaction
coordinator sends out to the paxos
followers a commit message saying look
please remember that permanently in the
transaction log that we're committing
this transaction and it also tells the
leaders of the other PACs those groups
involved in the transaction then they
can commit as well and so now this
leader sends out commit messages to his
followers as well as soon as the commits
are
the transaction coordinator probably
doesn't send out the commit message to
the other shards until it's committed as
safe in the log so that the transaction
coordinator is not guaranteed not to
forget its decision once commits these
commit messages are committed into the
paxos logs of the different shards each
of those shards can actually execute the
rights that is place the written data
and release the locks on the data items
so that other transactions can use them
and then the transactions over so first
of all please feel free to ask questions
if by raising your hand a few if you
have questions ok so there's some points
to observe about the design so far which
is only covered the readwrite aspect of
transactions one is that it's that the
locking that is insuring serializability
that is of two transactions conflict
because they use the same data one has
to completely wait for the other
releases locks before it can proceed so
it's using so spanners using completely
standard two-phase locking in order to
get serializability and completely
standard two-phase commit to get
distributed transactions the two-phase
commits widely hated because if the
transaction coordinator should fail or
become unreachable than any transactions
it was managing block indefinitely until
the transaction coordinator comes back
up and they block with locks help so
people have been in general very
reluctant to use two-phase commit in the
real world because it's blocking spanner
solves this by replicating the
transaction manager the transaction
manager itself is a Paxos replicated
state machine so everything it does like
for example remember whether it's
committed or not is replicated into the
paxos log so if the leader here fails
even though it was managing the
transaction because it's raft replicated
either of these two
replicas can spring to life take over
leadership and also take over being the
transaction manager and they'll have in
their law it's the transaction manager
decided to commit any leader that takes
over will see a commitment it's log and
be able to then tell the other right
away tell the other participants and
two-phase commit that look oh this
transaction was committed so this
effectively eliminates the problem a
two-phase commit that it can block with
locks held if there's a failure this is
a really big deal because this problem
basically makes two-phase commit
otherwise completely unacceptable for
any sort of large-scale system that has
a lot of parts that might fail the other
another thing to note is that there's a
huge amount of messages on in this
diagram here and that means that many of
them are across data centers and said
the some of these messages that go
between the shards or between a client
and a shard whose leaders in another
data center may take many milliseconds
and in a world in which you know
computations take nanoseconds this is
essentially pretty grim expense and
indeed you can see that from in table
six and table six if you look at it it's
describing the performance of a spanner
deployment where the different replicas
are on different sides of the United
States I east and west coast and it
takes about a hundred milliseconds to do
complete a transaction where the
different replicas involved are on
different coats that's a huge amount of
time it's a tenth of a second there's
maybe not quite as bad as it may seem
because the throughput of the system
since it's sharded and it can run a lot
of non conflicting transactions in
parallel the throughput may be very hard
high but their delay for individual
transactions very significant I mean a
hundred milliseconds is maybe somewhat
less than a human is going to notice but
if you have to do a couple of them to
just say generate a webpage or carry out
a human instruction it's starting to be
amount of time whoops
you noticeable start to be bothering
bothersome
on the other hand for I think I suspect
from many uses of spanner all the
replicas might be in in the same city or
sort of across town and they're the much
faster times that you can see in Table
three are relevant in the Earth's Table
three shows that it can complete
transactions where the data centers are
nearby in all right you know I think
it's 14 milliseconds instead of 100
milliseconds so that's not quite so that
nevertheless these read/write
transactions are slow enough that we'd
like to avoid the expense if we possibly
can so that's going to take us to
read-only transactions it turns out that
if you're not writing that is if you
know in advance that all of the
operations in a transaction are
guaranteed to be reads then spanner has
a much faster much more streamlined much
less massive message intensive scheme
for executing read-only transactions
okay so so read-only transactions start
a new topic the reader only transactions
work although they rely on some
information from readwrite transactions
to designs quite different from the read
of the readwrite transactions in spanner
eliminates two big costs and it's
read-only transaction design eliminates
two of the costs that were present and
readwrite transactions first of all as I
mentioned it reads from local replicas
and so if you have a replica as long as
there's a replica the DVD the client
needs the transaction needs in the local
data center you can do the read and from
that local replica which may take a
small fraction of a millisecond to talk
to instead of maybe dozens of
milliseconds if you have to go cross
country so it can read from local
replicas but node you know again a
danger here is that any given replicas
may not be up-to-date so there has to be
a story for that
and the other big savings and the
read-only design is that it doesn't use
locks it doesn't use two-phase commit I
mean that doesn't need a transaction
manager and this the voids things like
cross data center or inter data center
messages to PACs those leaders and
because no locks are taken out not only
does that make the read-only
transactions faster but it avoids
slowing down read only read write
transactions because they don't have to
rate for locks held by read-only
transactions now I mean just to kind of
preview why this is important to them
tables 3 & 6 show a ten times latency
improvement for read-only transactions
compared to readwrite transactions so
the main only design is submit factor
ten boost in latency and much less
complexity is almost certainly far more
throughput as well and the big challenge
is going to be how to square the you
know really transactions don't do a lot
of things that were quiet required and
we don't rewrite transactions to get
serialize ability so we need to find a
need to find a way to kind of square
this increased efficiency with
correctness and so there's really two
main correctness constraints that they
wanted to have read-only transactions
imposed the first is that they like all
transactions they still need to be
serializable and what that means is that
even though just a review even though
the system may execute transactions
concurrently in parallel the results
that a bunch of concurrent transactions
must yield both in terms of sort of
values that they return to the client
and modifications to the database the
results of a bunch of concurrent
transactions must be the same as some
one at a time or serial execution of
those transactions and for read-only
transactions what that essentially means
is that the an entire all the reads of a
read-only transaction must effectively
fit neatly between all the rights of a
bunch of transactions that can be viewed
as going before it
and and it must not see any of the
rights of the transactions that we're
going to view as it's going after it so
we need a way to sort of fit to read all
the reads of a transaction read-only
transaction kind of neatly between
readwrite transactions well the other
big constraint that the paper talks
about is that they want external
consistency and what this means it's
actually equivalent to linearise ability
that we've seen before what this really
means is that if one transaction commits
finishes committing and another
transaction starts after the first
transaction completed in real time then
the second transaction is required to
see the rights done by the first
transaction another way of putting that
is that transactions even read-only
transactions should not see stale data
and if there's a committed write from a
completed transaction that's prior to
the readonly transaction prior to the
start of the read-only transaction the
read-only transaction is required to see
that right ok so this is actually none
of neither of these is particularly
surprising but standard databases like
my sequel or something for example can
be configured to provide this kind of
consistency so in a way it's sort of the
consistency that if you didn't know
better this is exactly the consistency
that you would expect of a
straightforward system and in the you
know
have it but it makes programmers lives
it makes it much easier to produce
correct answers in otherwise you don't
have this kind of consistency then the
programmers are responsible for kind of
programming around whatever anomalies
the database may provide so this is like
a night this is sort of the gold
standard of correctness
okay so let's I want to gonna talk about
how we'd only transactions work it's a
bit of a complex story so I think what
I'd like to talk about first is to just
consider what would happen if we did
just absolutely the stupidest thing and
had the read-only transactions not do
anything special to achieve consistency
but just read the very latest copy of
the data so every time I read only
transaction does a read we could just
have it look at the local replicas and
find the current most up-to-date copy of
the data and that would be very
straightforward very low overhead so we
need to understand why that doesn't work
in order so this is a so why not read
the just a the latest value and so maybe
we'll imagine that the transaction is a
transaction that simply reads x and y
and prints them finance read-only I'm
going to print Y I'll just print X comma
Y
okay so all I want to show you an
example of a situation in which read
having this transaction is just simply
be the latest value yields incorrect not
not serializable results so suppose we
have three transactions running t1 t2 t3
t3 is going to be our transaction t1 and
t2 or transactions that are our rewrite
transactions so let's say that t1 right
sex and rights why and then commits and
you know maybe it's a bank transfer
operation so it's transferring money
from X to Y and we're printing x and y
because we're doing an audit of the bank
try to make sure it hasn't lost money
let's imagine that transaction 2 also
does another transfer between balances x
and y and then commits and now we have
our transaction transaction t3 it needs
to read x and y so it's gonna have a
read of X let's say the read of X
happens at this point in time and so I'm
the way I'm drawing these diagrams is
that real time moves to the right wall
clock time time you'd see on your watch
moves to the right so the read of X
happens here after transaction 1
completes before transaction 2 starts
and let's say T 3 is running on a slow
computer so it only manages to issue the
read of Y much later so the way this is
gonna play out is that transaction 3
will see the Y value that t1 wrote but
the x value that t2 wrote
assuming it uses this dubious procedure
of simply reading the latest value
that's in the database and so this is
not serializable because well we know
that any serial order that could exist
must have t1 followed by t2 there's only
2 places teeth rica go so t3 could go
here
can't fit here because if t3 was second
in the equivalent serial order then it
shouldn't see rights by t2 which comes
after it should see the value of Y
produced by t1 but it doesn't write it
see the value produced by t3 by t2 so
this is not an equivalent this serial
order wouldn't produce the same results
the only other one available to us is
this one this serial order would get the
same value for y that t3 actually
produced but if this was the serial
order then t3 should have seen the value
written by t2 but it actually saw the
valuable written by t1 so this execution
is not equivalent to any one at a time
searing the order so this is like
there's something broken about reads
simply reading the latest value so we
know that doesn't work you know what
we're really looking for of course is
that either the our our transaction
either reads the both values at this
point in time or it reads both values at
this point in time okay so the approach
that span our taste to this it's a
somewhat complex the first big idea is
an existing idea
it's called snapshot isolation
and the way I'm gonna describe this is
that let's imagine that all the
computers involved had synchronized
clocks that is you know they all have a
clock the clock wields yields us or wall
clock time like oh it's 143 in the
afternoon on April 7th 2020 so that's
what we mean by a wall clock time a time
so it's assumed that all the computers
assume even though this isn't true that
all the computers involved have
synchronized times furthermore let's
imagine that every transaction is
assigned a particular time a time stamp
and
time stamps their wall clocks times
taken from these synchronized clocks for
readwrite transaction its timestamp is
I'm going to say just for this for this
simplified design is the real time at at
the commit
and for read for a or at the time at
which the transaction manager starts the
commit and for read-only transaction the
timestamp is equal to the start time all
right so every turns out
time and we're gonna design our system
or a snapshot isolation system gets is
designed to execute as if to get the
same results as if all the transactions
had executed in timestamp order so we're
going to assign the transactions each
transaction a timestamp and then we're
going to arrange the executions so that
the transactions gets the results as if
they had executed in that order so given
the timestamps we sort of need to have
an implementation that will kind of
easily honor the timestamps and
basically you know show each transaction
the data sort of as it existed at its
timestamp okay so the way that this
works for read-only transactions is that
each replica when it stores data it
actually has multiple versions of the
data so we have a multiple version
database every database record has you
know maybe if it's been written a couple
times it has a separate copy of that
record for each of the times it's been
written
each one of them associated with the
timestamp of the transaction that wrote
it and then the basic strategies that
read only transactions when they when a
read-only transaction does a read it's
already allocated itself a timestamp
when it started and so it accompanies
its read request with its timestamp and
the whatever server that stores the
replicas of the data that the
transaction needs it's going to look
into its multi version database and find
the record that's being asked for that
as the highest time that's still less
than the timestamp specified by the
read-only transaction so that means to
be the only transaction sort of sees
data that is data as of the time as up
it's time jozin timestamp okay so this
is for this snapshot isolation idea
works for read-only transactions or
spanner uses it for read-only
transactions spinner users still uses
two-phase locking and two-phase commit
for readwrite transactions and so the
readwrite transactions allocate
timestamps for themselves a commit time
but other than that they work in the
usual way with locks and two-phase
commit where's the read-only
transactions access multiple versions in
the database and get the version that's
you know written by the has the
timestamp
that's highest that's still less than
the read-only transactions times date
and where this is going to get us is
that you know read-only transactions
will see all the rights of readwrite
transactions with lower timestamps and
none of the rights of read/write
transactions with higher tyst timestamps
okay so how would
isolation work out for our example
example that I had here before in which
we had a failure of serial
serializability because reading
transaction read before I read values
that were not between any two other be
bright transactions okay so this is an
our example but with snapshot isolation
I'm showing you this to show that the
snapshot isolation technique solves our
problem causes the read-only transaction
to be serializable so again we have
these two readwrite transactions t1 and
t2 and we have our transaction that's a
read-only transaction t1 and t2 right as
before they write and they commit but
now
they're allocating themselves timestamps
as of the commit time so in addition to
using two-faced command and two-phase
locking these read/write transactions
allocate a timestamp so let's imagine
that at the time of the commit T one
looked at the clock and saw that it the
time was ten I'm gonna use times of ten
and twenty and whatnot but you know you
should imagine times as being real times
like four o'clock in the morning on a
given day so let's say that T one sees
the time as 10 when it committed and T 2
sees that the commit time the time was
20 so I'm gonna write these transactions
chosen timestamp after the @ sign then
the database storage systems the span
our storage systems are going to store
when transaction 1 does its writes
they're gonna store a new sort of not
instead of overwriting in the current
value they're just gonna add a new copy
of this record with the timestamp so
it's gonna the database is going to
store away a new record this says the
value of x at time 10 is whatever it
happens to be let's say 9 the value of
record Y at time 10 is C 11 maybe we're
doing a transfer from X to Y similarly C
2 chose timestamp of 20 because that was
the real time at commit time and the
database is gonna remember a new set of
Records in addition these old ones it's
gonna say X at time 20 maybe we did a
another transfer from X to Y and Y at
time 20 equals 12 oh so now we have two
copies of each record at different times
now transaction 3 is gonna come along
and again it starts at about this time
and does a read of X and again it's
gonna be slow so you know it's not gonna
get around to reading wine till much
later much later in real time
however when transaction 3 started it
chose a timestamp by looking at the
looking at the current time and so let's
say since we know in real time that
transaction 3 started after transaction
one on before transaction 2
no it's got to have chosen a transaction
time somewhere between 10 and 20 and
let's suppose it started it time 15 and
chose timestamp 15 for itself so that
mean when it does the read of X it's
gonna send a request the local replica
that holds X and it's gonna accompany it
with it it's time stamp of 15 it's gonna
say please give me the latest data as of
time 15 of course transaction 2000
executed yet and but nevertheless the
highest time stamp copy of X is the one
from time 10 written by transaction 1 so
we're gonna get 9 for this one time
passes transaction 2 commits now
transaction 3 does the second read again
at a company suit the read requests with
its own time stamp of 15 Center the
server's now the server's have to
records but again because the server
gets transaction threes time stamp of 15
it looks at its records and say ha 15
sits between these two I'm gonna return
the highest time stamp record for X for
y it's less than the requested time
stamp and that's still the version of Y
from time 10 so the read of Y will
return at 11
that is the read of X essentially
happens at this time but because we
remembered a time stamp and we have the
database keep data as of different times
it was written
it's as if both reads happened the time
15 instead of one at time 15 and one
later and now you'll see that in fact
this just essentially emulates a serial
one at a time execution in which the
order is timestamp order transaction 1
and transaction - sorry then transaction
3 then transaction 2 that is a serial
order that is equivalent to that was
also actually produced is the time stamp
order of 10 15 20
alright okay so that's a simplified
version of what spanner does for really
transactions there's more complexity
which I'll get to in a minute
one question you might have is why it
was okay for transaction 3 to read an
old value of y that is it issued this
read of Y at this point in time the
freshest data for why was this value 12
but the value would actually got was
intentionally a stale value not the
freshest value but the value from a
while ago this value 11 so why is that
okay why is it okay not to be using the
freshest version of the data and the
kind of technical justification for that
is that transaction 2 and transaction 3
are concurrent that is the overlap in
time so those sort of time extent of
transaction 2 is here and the time
extent of transaction 3 is here they're
concurrent and the rules for linearise
ability and external consistency or that
if two transactions are concurrent then
the serial order that the database is
allowed to use can be can put the two
transactions in either order and here
the database spanner has chosen to put
transaction 3 before transaction 2 in
the serial order okay Robert we we have
a student question does external
consistency like with timestamps always
imply a strong consistency I'm
yes yes I think so
if strong consistency strong consistency
usually what people mean by that is
linearise ability and I believe the
definition of linearise ability and
external consistency are the same so I
would say yes and another question how
does this not absolutely blow up storage
that is a great question and the answer
is it definitely blows up storage and
the reason is that now the storage
system has to keep multiple copies data
records that have been recently modified
multiple times and that's definitely
expense both both this cost and storage
and space on the disk in the memory and
also it's just like an added layer of
bookkeeping you know now lookups have to
consider the timestamps as well as keys
the storage expense I think is not as
great as it could be because the system
discards old records that paper does not
say what the policy is but presumably
well it must be discarding old records
certainly if the only reason for the
multiple records is to implement
snapshot isolation of these kinds of
transactions then you don't really need
to remember values too far in the past
because you only need to remember values
back to the sort of earliest time that a
that a transaction could have started at
that's still running now and if your
transactions mostly you're always finish
or force the finish by killing them or
something within say one minute if no
transaction can take longer than a
minute then you only have to remember
the last minute of versions in the
database now in fact the paper implies
that they
day two farther back than that because
it appears they support intentionally
support these snapshot reads which allow
them to support the notion of seeing you
know data from a while ago you know
yesterday or something but they don't
say but but the garbage collection
policy is for old values so I don't know
how expensive it would be for them okay
okay so the the justification for ice
legal is that in external consistency
that the only rule that external
consistency imposes is that if one
transaction has completed then a
transaction that starts after it must
see its rights so t1 may be t1 completed
let's say that t1 completed at this time
and t3 started just after it may be
external consistency but demand that t3
sees key ones rights but since c2
definitely didn't finish before t3
started we have no obligation under
external consistency forty-three to see
teachers rights and indeed in this
example it does not so it's actually
legal um okay another problem that comes
up is that the transaction T 3 is needs
to read data as of a particular
timestamp but you know the reason why
this is desirable is that were it allows
us to read from the local replicas in
the same data center but maybe that
local replica is in the minority of
paxos followers that didn't see the
latest log records the leader so maybe
our local replicas maybe it's never even
seen you know never saw these rights to
X&Y at all it's still back at a version
from pine you know five or six or seven
and so if we don't do something clever
when we ask for the sort of highest
version record you know less than
timestamp 15 we may get some much older
version that's not actually the you
produced by transaction one which were
required to see
so the way he spanner deals with this is
with our notion of safe time and the
scoop is that each replica remembers you
know it's getting log records from its
taxes leader and the log records it
turns out that the paper arranges so
that the leader sends out log records
and strictly increasing timestamp order
so a replica can look at the very last
log record it's gotten from its leader
to know how up to dated it so if I ask
for a value as of timestamp 15 but the
replica has only gotten log entries from
my pax was leader a few times stamp 13
the replicas gonna make us delay it's
not gonna answer until it's gotten a log
record with time stamped 15 from the
leader and this ensures that replicas
don't answer a request for a given
timestamp until they're guaranteed to
know everything from the leader up
through that time stamp so this may
delay this may delay the reads okay
so the next question I've been assuming
I assumed in this discussion that the
clocks and all the different servers are
perfectly synchronized so everybody's
clock says you know 1001 and 30 seconds
at exactly the same time but it turns
out that you can't synchronize clocks
that precisely you it's basically
impossible to get perfectly synchronized
clocks and the reasons are reasonably
fundamental so the topic is time
synchronization which is sort of making
sure clocks say the same real time value
different clocks read the same value the
I'll tell the sort of fundamental
problem is that time is defined as
basically the time it says on a
collection of highly accurate expensive
clocks in a set of government
laboratories so we can't directly read
them although we can know is that these
government laboratories can broadcast
the time in various ways and the
broadcast take time and so it's some
time later some possibly unknown time
later we hear these announcements of
what the time it's own you know it may
all hear these announcements at
different times due to varying delays so
I actually first don't want to consider
the problem of what the impact is if on
snapshot isolation if the clocks are not
synchronize which they won't be
okay so what if the clocks are
there's actually no problem at all for
the spanners readwrite transactions
because the readwrite transactions used
locks and two-phase commit they're not
actually using snaps out of a solution
so they don't care so the readwrite
transactions will still be serialized by
the lock the two-phase locking mechanism
so we're only interested in what happens
for an RF or read-only transaction so
let's suppose a read-only transaction
chooses a timestamp that is too large so
that is far in the future you know it's
now 12:01 p.m. and it chooses a
timestamp at C 1 o'clock p.m. so if a
transactions chosen timestamps too big
that's actually not that bad what it'll
mean is that it will do read requests
it'll send a read request to some
replicas the replicas would say wait a
minute you're you know your clock is
Farrer it's far greater your chime seems
far greater than the last log entry I
saw for my pax was leader so I'm gonna
make you wait until the PAX was at the
time and the log entries and the Paxos
leader catches up to the time you've
requested I'm only gonna respond then so
this is correct but slow the reader will
be forced away that's not the worst
in the world but what happens if we have
a read-only transaction and it's
timestamp is too small and this would
correspond to its clock being less
either set wrong so that it's said in
the past or maybe it was originally set
correctly but the clock its clock ticks
too slowly the problem with this this is
a obviously causes a correctness problem
this will cause a violation of external
consistency because the multi version
databases you'll give it a timestamp
that's far in the past say an hour ago
and the database will read you a value
associated with it the timestamp from an
hour ago which may ignore more recent
writes so using a assigning a timestamp
to a transaction that's too small will
cause you to miss recent committed
writes and that's a violation of
external consistency so not externally
so so we actually have a problem here
the assumption that the clocks were
synchronized is in fact a very serious
assumption and the fact that you cannot
count on it means that unless we do
something the system is going to be
incorrect all right so so can we
synchronize clocks perfectly all right
that would be the ideal thing and if not
why not so so what about clock
synchronization the as I mentioned we're
done come from this it's actually a
collection of the kind of median of a
collection of clocks and government labs
the way that we hear about the time is
that it's broadcast by various protocols
sometimes by radio protocols like
basically what GPS is doing for spanner
is a GPS acts as a radio broadcast
system that broadcasts the current time
from some government lab through the GPS
satellites to GPS receiver sitting in
the Google machine rooms and there's a
number of other radio protocols like WWB
is another older radio protocol for
broadcasting the current time and
there's newer protocols like there's
this NTP protocol that operates over the
Internet that also is in charge of
basically broadcasting time so the sort
of system diagram is that there are some
government labs and the government labs
with their accurate clocks define a
universal notion of time that's called
UTC so we've UTC coming from some clocks
in some labs then we have some you know
radio internet broadcast or something
for the case of spanner it's the we can
think of the government allowed to
broadcasting to GPS satellites the
satellites in turn broadcast and the
broadcaster you know the millions of GPS
receivers that are out there
you can buy GPS receivers for a couple
hundred bucks that will decode the
timestamps in the in the GPS signals and
sort of keep you up to date with exactly
what the time is corrected for the
propagation delay between the government
labs and the GPS satellites and also
corrected for the delay between the GPS
satellites in your current position and
then there's in each data center there's
a GPS receiver that's connected up to
what the paper calls a time master which
is some server there's going to be more
than one of these for data center in
case one fails and then there's all the
hundreds of servers in the data center
that are running spanner either as
servers or as clients each one of them
is going to periodically send a request
saying aw what time is it to the local
one or more usually more than one piece
one feels to the time masters and the
time master will reply with oh you know
I think the current time has received
for GPS is such-and-such now built into
this unfortunately is a certain amount
of uncertainty and the primary sources
of uncertainty I think well there's
there's fundamentally uncertainty in
that we don't actually know how far we
are from the GPS satellites exactly so
the you know radio signals take some
amount of time even though the GPS
satellite knew exactly what time it is
those signals take some time to get to
our GPS receiver we're not sure what
that is that means that when the Jeep we
get a message from the radio message
from the GPS satellite saying exactly 12
o'clock
you know if the propagation delay might
have been you know a couple of
nanoseconds that mean that's there were
actually the propagation delays much
more than that it's really uncertainty
in the propagation delay means that
we're not really sure exactly whether
it's 12 o'clock or a little before a
little after in addition all the times
at time is communicated there's
did uncertainty that you have to account
for and the biggest sources are that
when a server sends requests after a
while it gets a response if the response
says it's exactly 12 o'clock but the
amount but um say a second pass you know
between when the server sent the request
and when I got the response all the
server knows is that even if the master
had the correct time all the server
knows is that the time is within a
second of 12 o'clock because maybe that
may be the request was instant but the
reply was delayed or maybe the request
was delayed by a second and the response
was the incident so all you really know
is that it's between you know 12 o'clock
and zero seconds and twelve o'clock and
one second okay so there's always this
uncertainty and in order to which we
really can't ignore though because the
uncertainties we're talking about
milliseconds here and we're gonna find
out that these that the uncertainty and
the time goes directly to the these how
long these safe waits have to be and how
long some other pauses have to be the
commit wait as we'll see so you know
uncertainty in the level of milliseconds
is a serious problem the other big
uncertainty is that each of these
servers only request the current time
from the master every once in a while
say every minute or however often and
between that the each server runs its
own local clock that sort of keeps the
time starting with the last time from
the master those local clocks are
actually pretty bad and can drift by
things by milliseconds between times
that the server talks to the master and
so the system has to sort of add the
unknown but estimated drift of the local
clock to the uncertainty of the time so
I'm in order to capture this uncertainty
and account for it
spanner uses this true time scheme in
which when you ask what time it is what
you actually get back as one of these TT
interval things which is a pair of an
earliest time and a latest earliest time
is their early early as the time could
possibly be and the second is the latest
the time can possibly be so when the
application you know makes this library
call that asked for the time it gets
back this payer all it knows is that the
current time is somewhere between
earliest and latest that's what you know
earliest might be in this case earliest
might be twelve o'clock and may this
might be twelve o'clock in one second
just just our guarantee that the that
the correct time isn't less than
earliest and isn't greater than latest
what we don't know where between
otherwise okay
so this is what uh when a transaction
asks the system what time it is this is
this is what the transaction actually
gets back from the time system and now
let's return to our original problem was
that if the clock was too slow that a
read-only transaction might read data
too far in the past and that it wouldn't
read data from a recent committed
transaction so we need to know what
we're looking for is how spanner uses
these TT intervals in its notion of true
time in order to ensure that despite
uncertainty in what time it is
transaction a external consistency that
is a read-only transaction it's
guaranteed to see writes done by a
transaction rate transaction that
completed before us and there are two
rules that the paper talks about that
conspire to enforce this and the two
rules which are in section 4-1 - one of
them is the start rule
and the other is commit wait
this note rule tells us what time stamps
trains actually what time stamps
transactions choose and basically says
that a transactions timestamp has to be
equal to the latest half of the true
time current time so this is T T now
call which returns one of those earliest
latest pairs that's the current time and
that transactions timestamp has to be
the latest that is it's going to be a
time that's guaranteed not to have
happened yet because the true time is
between earliest and latest and for a
read-only transaction it's a sign the
latest time as of its the time it starts
and for a read or write transaction is
to assign a timestamp this latest value
as of the time it starts to commit
okay so the start rule says this is how
spanner chooses time stamps the commit
weight rule only for readwrite
transactions says that when a
transaction coordinator is you know
collects the votes and sees that it's
able to commit and and chooses a time
stamp after it chooses this time stamp
it's required to delay to wait a certain
amount of time before til I have to
actually commit and write the values and
release locks so a readwrite transaction
has to delay until it's time stamps that
it chose when it was starting to think
about commit is less than the current
time the earliest
sorry
so what's going on here is the
sits in a loop calling TS now and it
stays in that loop until the timestamp
that it had chosen at the beginning of
the commit process is less than the
current times earliest half and what
this guarantees is that since now the
earliest possible correct time is
greater than the transactions timestamp
that means that when this loop is
finished when the commit wait is
finished this time stamp of the
transaction is absolutely guaranteed to
be in the past okay so how does the
system actually make use of these two
rules in order to enforce external
consistency for read-only transactions I
want to go back to our or I want to cook
up a someone simplified scenario in
order to illustrate this so I'm gonna
imagine that the writing transactions
only do one write each just reduce the
complexity let's say that there's two
read/write transactions so we have t0
and t1 are read/write transactions and
they both write X and we have a t2 which
is going to read X and we want to make
sure that t2 sees you know it's going to
use snapshot isolation on timestamps we
want to make sure that sees the latest
written value so we're going to imagine
that t2 does a write of X and writes one
to X and then commits we're going to
imagine that
sorry t1 write sex and come at t2 also
writes X writes a value 2 to X and we
need to distinguish between can prepare
and commit so we're going to say it it's
really a prepare that the transaction
chooses its timestamps so this is a
point at which it chooses timestamp and
it commits some time later and then
we're imagining by assumption that t2
starts after t1 finishes so it's going
to read X
afterwards and we want to make sure it
sees - all right so let's suppose that
t0 chooses a time stamp of one commits
writes the database let's say t1 starts
at the time it chooses a time stamp it's
gonna get some it's not get a single
number from the true time system really
gets a range of numbers you know
earliest and a latest value let's say at
the time it chooses its time stamp it
the range of values that earliest time
it gets is 1 and the latest field in the
current time is 10 so the rule says that
it must choose 10 the latest value as
its time stamp so t1 is gonna commit
with its time step 10
now you can't commit yet because the
commit weight rule says it has to wait
until it's time stamp is guaranteed to
be in the past so transaction 1 is going
to sit there keep asking what time is it
what time is it
until it gets an interval back that
doesn't include time 10 so at some point
it's gonna ask what time it is is gonna
get a time that we're the earliest
values 11 and elitist is I don't know
let's say 20 and now I was gonna say AHA
now I know that my time Sam it's
guaranteed to be in the past and I can
commit so t1 will actually this is its
commit wait period to sit there and wait
for a while before it commits okay now
after it commits transaction two comes
along a monster B Dex it's gonna choose
a time stamp also we're assuming that it
starts after t1 finishes because that's
the interesting scenario for external
consistency so let's say when it asks
for the time it asks at a time after
time 11 so it's going to get back an
interval that includes time 11
so let's suppose it gets back in a
little bit goes from time ten this is
the earliest and time twelve the latest
and of course the time twelve has to be
since we know that must be at least time
11 since transaction two started after
transaction one finished that means that
the 11th must be less than the latest
value transaction 2 is going to choose
this latest 1/2 as its timestamp so it's
gonna actually choose timestamp 12 and
in this example when it does its read
it's gonna ask the storage system oh I
want to read as of timestamp 12 since
transaction 1 wrote with timestamp 10
that means that you know assuming the
safe wait the safe time machinery works
we're actually gonna read the correct
value and what's going on here is that
the so this happened to work out but
indeed it's guaranteed to work out if
transaction 2 as long as transaction 2
starts after transaction 1 commits and
the reason is that commit weight causes
transaction 1 not to finish committing
until its timestamp is guaranteed to be
in the past
all right so transaction 1 chooses a
timestamp it's guaranteed to commit
after that timestamp transaction 2
starts after the commit it and so we
don't know anything about what its
earliest value will be but its latest
value is guaranteed to be after the
current time but we know that the
current time is after the commit time of
T 1 and therefore that teaches latest
value the timestamp it chooses is
guaranteed to be after when C committed
and therefore after the timestamp that C
used and because transaction 2 if
transaction 2 starts after T 1 finishes
transaction 2 is guaranteed to get a
higher timestamp
and the snapshot isolation machinery the
multiple versions will cause it to read
to it's read to see all lower valued
writes from all the lower time-stamped
transactions that means teach you is
going to see t1 nom and that basically
means that we're this this is how
spanner enforces external consistency
for its transactions so any questions
about this machinery alright um I'm
gonna step back a little bit there's
really from my point of view sort of two
big things going on here one is snapshot
isolation by itself snapshot isolation
by itself is enough to give you that
it's keeping the multiple versions and
giving every transaction a timestamp
snapshot isolation is guaranteed to give
you serializable read-only transactions
because basically what snapshot
isolation means is that we're going to
use these timestamps as the equivalent
serial order and things like the safe
wait the safe time ensure that read-only
transactions really do read as of their
time stamps see every readwrite
transaction before that and none after
that so there's really two pieces
snapshot isolation snapshot isolation by
itself though is actually often used not
just by spanner but generally doesn't by
a self guarantee external consistency
because in a distributed system it's
different computers choosing the
timestamp so we're not sure there's
timestamps will obey external
consistency even if they'll deliver
serialize ability so in addition to
snapshot isolation spanner also has
synchronized timestamps and it's the
synchronized timestamps plus the commit
weight rule that allow spanner to
guarantee external consistency as well
as serializability and again the reason
why all this is interesting is that
programmers really like transactions and
I really like external consistency
because that makes the applications much
easier to write
they traditionally not been provided in
distributed settings because they're too
slow and so the fact that spanner
manages to release make read-only
transactions very fast is extremely
attractive right no locking no two-phase
commit and not even any distant reads
for a read-only transactions they
operate very efficiently from the local
replicas and again this is what's good
for a basically attend factor of 10
latency improvement as measured in
tables 3 & 6 but just to remind you it's
not all it's not all fabulous the the
all this wonderful machine it really
only applies to read-only transactions
readwrite transactions still use
two-phase commit and locks and there's a
number of cases in which even spanner
will have the block like due to the safe
time and the commit wait but as long as
their times are accurate enough
these commit weights are likely to be
relatively small okay just to summarize
the spanner at the time was kind of a
breakthrough because it was very rare to
see deployed systems that operate
distributed transactions where the data
was geographically in very different
data centers I'm surprising you know
spanner people were surprised that
somebody was using a database that
actually did a good job of this and that
the performance was tolerable and the
snapshot isolation and a timestamp being
part of the probably the most
interesting aspects of the paper and
that is all I have to say for today any
last questions okay
I think on
we're gonna we're going to see farm
which is a sort of very different slice
through the desire to provide very high
performance transactions so I'll see you
on Thursday