okay so we're in the middle of
explaining Bitcoin design and I've
gotten to the point of ask of wanting
there to be a global published record of
all the transactions all right okay and
this is this requirement is very similar
to the requirement for certificate
transparency from last week and the
solution is somewhat reminiscent
although more sophisticated then
certificate transparency solution and a
name we want a public log this is often
also called a public ledger okay so how
are we going to build ourselves a public
ledger so that everybody agrees on all
the transactions that have already
happened and further when they agree on
the order of the transactions because if
Y tries to send this coin to both Z and
Q at the same time you know we want the
first one to win and the second one to
be ignored
whatever Yellin which one want which
transaction was came first and which
came second and should be ignored okay
so how to make a ledger so here's a bad
idea
well a good idea actually have the most
simplest idea is to just pick somebody
who everybody trusts and have that
somebody maintain the ledger for you
every time you want to do transaction
you tell the trusted entity what the
transaction is it just accumulates a log
and it's willing to give a copy of that
log to anyone so anyone can inspect it
and see if coins already been spent and
that actually is a good idea and if you
could possibly do it you should for
various reasons the Bitcoin designers
rejected this very obvious
straightforward idea and the fundamental
reason is that in a big system in a
worldwide system there's unlikely to be
any single entity that everyone trusts
and that is indeed trustworthy and has
no corrupt employees for example and in
a global system you know that means that
we can't have the United States you know
government
I'm the trusted entity because there's
plenty of governments in the world to
don't necessarily trust the United
States similarly for any other
individual government so really for a
global system there's no it's it's easy
to argue against the idea of having a
single central trusted entity so that
leaves us way as well we want to run the
system make a system that's built out of
mutually untrusting participants where
we can survive malice by you know by
their participants okay so here's a
here's a bad possibility let's just let
anybody let's build a system on which
anybody can join so it's gonna have
thousands maybe if computers will call
them peers they're scattered all over
the Internet
and each one of them is going to be
running the software to for our new
cryptocurrency system anytime somebody
wants to have a new transaction like Y
wants to send a coin to Z Y floods their
new transaction sends their new
transaction to all the peers to send
them directly or another design which is
actually what Bitcoin uses is that Y
sends a new transaction to a couple the
peers and then the peers afford it sort
of over individual TCP links to the
entire rest of the system so in every
transaction ends up being sent to all
the peers and the peers what they're
trying to do is each of them maintain a
complete copy of the log of all
transactions and what we really want is
for all the peers used all the honest
peers for their transaction logs to be
identical they'll agree on which
transactions exist and just as important
on the order of those transactions so
how can we arrange for all these peers
to end up processing the heading
transactions they're logs in the same
order remember of course why may have
sent the transaction to Z you know to
these peers and at the same time sent
its transaction to Q to some other set
of peers and we want to make sure that
despite that the peers end up with the
same with identical logs even if Y is
trying to treat well I actually don't
know how to design this one possibility
that you can imagine is that the peers
would somehow talk to each other about
each new transaction and for each new
slot in the log would vote on what
transaction should fill that slot and
have the majority you know since they
may disagree legitimately if they
received different transactions we have
a majority rule that says well we're
gonna all the peers are gonna look at
all the votes and the transaction that
gets the most votes is the one that will
go in the next slot in the log and then
they'll vote again on the next slide and
you know maybe you could get this to
work you'd have to know who all the
other peers are in order to know what a
majority is you don't have to know how
many peers there are and you really want
to make sure that you never count any
peer more than once but in a completely
open system like Bitcoin actually we
can't do either of those things we don't
know how many participants there are in
Bitcoin and furthermore the number
changes all the time as people peers
join and leave the system so we don't
know how many peers are so we don't know
what a majority would be furthermore we
don't have a way to reliably count votes
such that each participant only gets one
vote even assuming that was desirable
for example so we can't use IP addresses
in order to decide it's distinct votes
we can't say well each IP address gets
one vote or at most one vote because it
turns out to be extremely easy to either
forge I P addresses or by breaking into
people's computers to accumulate tens of
thousands of real computers that you can
control and you of course would you can
get them all to vote on your
and you can get them all to vote in the
system so an attacker could probably
accumulate a majority of votes
relatively easily in a sort of
straightforward design like this and if
an attacker can can get a majority of
the votes then it can use this majority
to sit to sort of say different things
conflicting things but with the majority
each time so if Z asks the system oh you
know with which which of the two
transactions came first cuz you know
that remember the problem were worried
about is that y is gonna double spend
some coin so it's gonna spend the same
coin - Q wants you to believe that and
it's gonna send that same Q's coin to Z
and 1c to believe that so maybe when Q
asks what's the next transaction to log
the majority controlled by the attacker
can say oh you know wise transfer to Q
is the very next one in the log and that
comes before this transaction and when Z
asks maybe the attackers majority will
say well you know the transfer Z comes
first and this other transaction to Q
comes second and that would mean the
attacker can trick q + Z into X into
accepting the same coin that's a double
spend and that's a disaster so without
some very clever idea it's very hard to
build an open system
you know without a controlled
memberships very hard to build an open
system in which you have reliable voting
okay but in fact Bitcoin doesn't quite
use voting but it nevertheless manages
to solve this problem of how to get
agreement on a single ledger
despite malice so this is the Bitcoin
blockchain
and at this point there's a lot of diff
chain systems out there so actually I'm
not even sure what blockchain as a term
refers to but I'm only talking about
Bitcoin right now okay so the goal is we
want agreement on a single transaction
log again because we want to prevent
double spending and this we're going to
be building Bitcoin builds this thing
called the blockchain that contains all
the transactions on all the coins so
it's a single a single blockchain that
describes all the transactions in the
system again as with the previous system
there's going to be many peers so we
still have this kind of overlay network
appears each peer is kind of building a
copy of the log and a complete copy of
the transaction log in its own memory
and we don't know how many peers they
are or how many there are who they are
but they form a sort of in one of these
overlay networks spotted with TCP
connections and anytime a peer hears
about a new transaction like when Y
wants to submit a payment transaction to
Z or Q it's gonna send it to one or more
peers and that peers gonna flood the
transaction over the whole system the
way the log is built up the way that
blockchain is built up is that each of
the peers accumulates transactions and
PACs many transactions thousands into a
block and then it's entire new blocks of
transactions that are really appended to
the ledger again by flooding new blocks
over the whole system so that at least
in theory every peer sees every new
blocks so the blockchain model
blockchains consists of blocks what each
block looks like is the hash of the
previous block it's a bit like my
previous transaction broken transaction
system so we have the hash of the
previous block like cryptographic hash
of the previous block there's a set of
transactions so these are individual
spans from you know why is trying to pay
queue or whatever it happens to be a
couple hundred of whole thousand
individual transactions and each
transaction is actually much as I
described before it has the hash of the
previous transaction for that coin which
is going to exist in a previous block
typically it has deprived a signature by
the private key of the previous owner of
that coin and it is the public key of
the new owner so this transaction would
have that transfers money from why the
queue would contain Hugh's public key
and a signature by with wise private key
plus a hash of a previous transaction in
a previous block as well as these
transactions there's a nonce
which I'll talk about in a moment it's
just a 32-bit number and then the
current time roughly the way the system
works is that the peers accumulate new
transactions and roughly every 10
minutes one of them produces a new block
that should be the successor block
containing all the transactions that
have been sort of sent into the system
in the ten minutes roughly since the
previous block was created and if you're
if somebody tells you they're paying you
Bitcoin then before you accept that
they've really done it you need to watch
the blockchain as it evolves and you
know blocks new blocks are signs
everywhere so the blockchain is quite
public if you think somebody claims to
have paid you you need to watch the
blockchain until you see a new block
that contains the transaction that
you're expecting from the person that
claimed to sent you money and with your
public key at them that looks a valid
you know correctly signed okay so
everybody everybody has to watch the
blockchain for payments to them all
right so who creates each block this
action of creating a new block is called
mining and the technique that's used to
produce a new block is often also called
proof of work in the sense that it
requires a lot of CPU time to produce a
new block and so the production of a new
block essentially proves that you
control a real live CPU and you're not
just mining new blocks on a fake
computer the new block
in order to be valid a new block when
you hash it has to have a certain number
of zeros at the beginning of the hash of
the block now of course if you just take
a bunch of arbitrary transactions and
you do a cryptographic hash on it it's
highly unlikely that the hash of some
just whatever data is gonna have more
than one or two or three zeros at the
beginning of the cryptographic hash
however the computer that's mining the
block can put any value it likes here
for the knots and so what the mining
computers do is that they try different
by different random values for the nonce
just pick one with a random number
generator that'll stick it in there copy
of the block they're trying to mine and
then they'll compute the hash on the
block
and they'll check how many zeros how
many leading zeros are in the hash with
this particular knots if it's enough
leading zeros I don't know how many it
is but it's you know sort of on the
order of dozens if there's enough
leading zeros and it's a valid mine a
valid block and the whatever peer it was
that found this nonce that caused the
block hash to have lots of leading zeros
can flood this block over the network
and you know all that's being equal
that'll be the new next block and the
chain but typically the the hash of the
block with any given nonce you know
won't have enough leading zeros and the
mining the peer will have to try another
nonce another random nonce keep doing
that until it gets uh a block that
hashes to a hash with enough leading
zeros and so this takes a lot of CPU
time it takes oh you know it's a random
process but the system is sort of tuned
and the number of zeros that are
required to exist at the beginning of
the hash of the block is set so that it
takes about ten minutes you know with
all the different peers hundreds of
thousands appears out there who are
doing Bitcoin mining the average amount
of time before the first one of them
finds a nonce for a block that has
enough feeding zeros is set up to be ten
minutes
okay so question how do peers or new
peers discover other peers to
communicate with yeah it's a great
question so this is sort of a reference
to the this network of Bitcoin peers if
I'm a new peer you know I've install a
new computer I get Bitcoin software
installed on my my computer and I want
to join the Bitcoin network how do I
know who to talk to and how do I know
well so the straightforward answer to
that is that the Bitcoin software has
built into it on the IP addresses of a
whole bunch of current peers and so your
software when you first fire it up into
the binary the source whatever the
Bitcoin software you know has a whole
bunch of IP addresses and you try to
make TCP connections to those existing
peers and if all goes well you'll be
able to connect to them and you'll say
look I'm new please give me a copy of
the blockchain as it exists now and
they'll send you the current block team
which is about a couple hundred
gigabytes right now so that's if all
goes well if all doesn't go well then
you may run into problems like for
example if your copy of the software has
been modified by somebody malicious to
have a list of IP addresses that are all
controlled by the attacker or the
attacker controls your computer network
so that regardless of who you try to
connect to you end up actually talking
to the attackers machines it may be that
the attacker is running you know their
own isolated network and that you know
you think your newly installed software
thinks it's made a bunch of connections
the Bitcoin knows but whoops they're all
attackers nodes in that case a
blockchain you'll get will be watching
controlled by the attacker
and you may well you will be in trouble
and you know there's pick one of some
defenses against this may be the main
well he
loaded correct Bitcoin software the
correct Bitcoin software has built-in
hashes of recent blocks in the
blockchain and that means that if you
connect to some attackers in your
running proper Bitcoin software at least
the Bakhtin has to start with the first
however many thousand blocks in the box
beam have to be correct if you download
it absolutely wrong software modified by
the attacker then there's just nothing
Bitcoin can do to help you then this is
a potential weakness in the system I
haven't necessarily heard of anybody
exploiting this but it's definitely
something to think about
ok back to mining ok so the if you want
to create a new block you gotta find a
nonce that causes the new block you're
trying to produce causes hash to have
lots of leading zeros for an individual
machine you know the amount of time for
an individual ordinary computer to find
a nonce that satisfies this requirement
is like at least in a months of CPU time
but there's a very large number of
Bitcoin miners out there and so even
though any one of them would take a very
long time to find a new block or we
really care about is the time for the
very first one of them to find a block
and since they're all making these sort
of random choices of nonce one of them
is gonna find a a nonce that fulfills
the requirements relatively soon and the
number a Bitcoin adjusts the number of
leading required leading zeros in the
hash in response to how fast new blocks
seemed to be appearing and so if new
blocks are appearing much faster than
once every 10 minutes Bitcoin will
automatically increase the number of
leading zeros that's required and
that'll make it correspondingly harder
and take longer for the miners to find a
a new block Nana blocks are of course
arriving slower than every 10 minutes
over a sustained period of time then
Bitcoin will adjust the required number
of leading zeroes in the hash to be
smaller and that means it'll be easier
quicker
to find you blocks to the sort of an
adaptive scheme there to us blocks to
new boxes show up run once every ten
minutes roughly okay so this is the
proof-of-work scheme and this is
essentially a solution and all in a
funny way to the that voting problem I
mentioned a few minutes ago where you
can't really have some practice I have
majority votes because we're not sure
who the participants are or how many
there are because people may sort of
create fake computers fake IP addresses
whatever it will here you have to use
CPU time which is a sort of real
resource that cannot be faked in order
to contribute a new block and that means
that um you know while it's not really a
voting scheme the what it's essentially
doing is the new block gets to come from
a reactively random choice over the
different computers that are involved in
in mining so this scheme is it's a sort
of a random sort of cryptographically
reasonably strong random selection
process for who gets to choose the next
block and so if there's a small number
of attackers they're highly unlikely to
be selected by this process in order to
contribute the next block now what that
means is that if most of the
participants or most of the CPU power in
the system is controlled by non
malicious people then most of the new
blocks will be found by non malicious
people and that's not an immediate
solution to double spending but we'll
see that it that it's the key to the
double spending defense okay
all right so let's go back to our
example we have a blockchain that maybe
looks like we currently block five
o'clock fine has been published to
everybody the mmm them all the peers are
working on mining a potential block six
and we don't know what's going to be yet
because because the miners are still
working on finding about knots but you
know we know that it has a bunch of
transactions in it well if at this point
why broadcasts you know say it's payment
to Z well the the miner is already
working on this block so wise new
transaction and even if it sends it out
so now probably not going to be
incorporated in the block has been
currently mind but all the miners will
kind of keep this new transaction and a
buffer on the side and when one of them
does find a new block for block 6 then
wise transaction will be incorporated
into the attempts to mine block seven as
soon as somebody does mind box seven
this Y arrow Z will actually be really
in the blockchain alright so so one
question is could there be two different
successors to walk six could there be
sort of a block seven and a block seven
prime right what prevents this structure
from arising and of course the reason
why we're interested in this is that if
the structure could arise then
then these two maybe seven prime B seven
double prime then these two different b7
s two different successive successors to
b6 might have different transfers from Y
and so if you were aware of just b7
prime you'd think why paid it's Bitcoin
to see if you were we're only a b7 prime
prime you this would click a totally
legitimate payment from wide acute my
question is can there be two different
successors to a block it turns out the
answer is yes and it's actually does
happen reasonably frequently and the
reason is that there's you know
thousands of peers out there Mining away
trying to find the successors to block
six and they're likely mining it's you
know trying to produce somewhat
different blocks with different sets of
transactions in them so it's easy to
imagine a situation in which some of the
peers you know they happen to see just
because of the way the transactions move
through the network they happen to see
why it's transferred to Z first and
incorporated in to block their mining
and other peers you know for sort of the
same successors but the their version of
the block their mining as a successor to
six just happen to have seen this
transaction first and included that in
the block so we can easily get different
miners trying to work in a way trying to
produce different successors to be six
if two of them happen to find a nonce
that satisfies the leading zeros in the
hash rule at the same time that means we
have two different blocks to tumor
totally valid blocks produced at the
same time and they're both going to send
those blocks out into the network and
they'll be seeing that you know on
roughly the same time by all the other
peers so it could easily be the case
that two different two quite different
successors to block six may arise and
it's called the fork
and so we're very interested in what
happens to Forks because this can and
does arise well the most immediate rule
is that as soon as any peer sees a
successor oh you know all the peers are
trying to mine a successor to block six
as soon as than ever any of them any of
them sees a new successor block be
flooded from some peer that did
successfully mine
it'll stop working on six and
immediately switch to trying to work on
a successor from b737 so initially every
peer as soon as it sees a successor
block switches to mining a successor for
that successor block so in this
situation some of the peers will see b7
Prime first and start working on a
successor to that then other peers will
start mine will see b7 prime prime for
it's just depending on you know what
they happen to see first if the if these
two are mined at the same time and
they'll start working on a successor to
b7 prime prime so now we got some of the
peers working on sort of extending this
fork in the blockchain and the other
peers working on extending this fork in
the blockchain however another critical
rule is that if a if somebody's mining
away on this trying to make one of these
blocks and it sees a new block for a
different fork that's longer then
anybody working on extending this fork
will switch to extending this longer
fork so that's a rule in the software
that everybody is supposed to favor the
longest chain so at least initially if
we have some of the peers mining a way
on one fork and the other and there's
the same length and others mining on the
other fork it turns out the variance in
how long it takes to produce a valid
knots is pretty high
so it's even if there's equal number of
peers mining both Forks it's highly
likely that one of them will find a
successor significantly before the other
and so this successor will be flooded to
a bunch of nodes appears that were
working on this successor and they'll
all switch to the longer Fork and so
that means that there's sort of an
asymmetry here that causes us a slight
you know with if this Fork itza gets
extended by the minor slightly before
this fork then that'll contract miners
over onto this fork it'll be more and
more miners mining on this Fork and so
the new blocks will be found more and
more rapidly on the winning fork so
there's a tendency sort of reinforced
success that's the longer fork gets
longer and pretty soon once all the
miners have heard about this longer fork
nobody will be left the mining on this
fork everybody will ignore it and
everybody will only treat this longest
fork as the real as the real chain okay
so this is it's highly likely that one
of the there's a fork that one of the
two Forks will see an x-block first will
be longer everybody all the peers will
switch to mining on it and that
everybody will rapidly agree that one of
the other is the longest fork of course
the transactions on the abandoned fork
you know usually most of the trend
usually these two competing blogs have
you know pretty much pretty similar set
of transactions but there may well be
transact a few transactions here that
were not there and certainly if
somebody's trying that will spend or but
if there are transactions in the
abandoned fork that didn't happen also
to be in the winning fork then these
transactions they just go away there's
no attempt in the sort of blockchain
system itself to try to carry over these
transactions now with it or there's no
attempt to kind of directly merge the
two forks now in fact you know if you
don't see your transaction show up you
maybe issue it
and you know because the blockchain is
public it'll become apparent that your
transaction needs to be reassured
because it wasn't incorporated more in
the winning fork however it is also the
case that for a brief period of time
both of these transactions were in the
blockchain right so for a brief period
of time there was a double spending of
wise coin in the blockchain and that you
know that's like a little bit of a
dangerous situation in fact you know
it's an extremely dangerous situation
right since the whole point was to avoid
block chains right until one of these
two chains got longer now it was totally
unclear which of these two chains to
believe and then these some of the peers
may only know about one of them or the
other of them so this raises a sort of
unhappy question about how Q or Z you
know what procedure should they use to
be sure that they've actually been paid
right apparently it's not enough for Z
to say well as soon as the transaction
appears in the blockchain then I'm sure
I didn't paint because that's not true
right maybe the maybe this bar chain
would end up being a shorter one and the
wipies Q blockchain will win similarly P
you can't just look at oh you know my
transaction showed up in this block and
the blockchain therefore it's a valid
transaction because it may end up being
abandoned due to being on a shorter fork
and so this is the reason for the rule
in that people who care don't really
believe in transactions until there's a
couple of blocks after them in the
blockchain and as a as the longer chain
gets longer and longer or as what you
think is the longer chain gets longer
and longer the chances that there might
be some other chain that will become
longer in it longer than it could
vanishingly small because if you're on a
slightly longer chain that's going to
attract miners to mining on it so no
other chain can grow very rapidly and of
course the you know the rate in which a
chain a particular fork can grow is
proportional to the number of peers that
are mining on that chain
all right so this is this is the
mechanism that prevents with it makes it
so that if Y sends out two conflicting
transaction that's at the same time even
though there can be a brief double spend
if there's a fork it will rapidly be
only one or the other of the two
transactions will be in the longest
chain and so one of them will win in the
sort of official chain now and you know
indeed if if this second transaction
shows up is sent to peers later on after
the Y transfer disease in the chain then
all the peers will ignore trend newly
arriving transactions that for coins
that have already been spent in a
transaction on the chain on the fork
that they're mining for so why can't you
know send out this transaction again
after the first transactions shows up in
the chain in the blockchain okay okay so
you know there's some other attacks you
might wonder about one question is
whether you know let's suppose that this
is the this is the chain if Y is
colluding with some peers and this is
the official b7 and we have a b8 etc you
know
supposing why isn't League with some of
the peers could appear take this block
seven it's now you know in the middle of
the chain and change it to produce just
a different block that doesn't have this
transaction in it and just sort of
substitute this new block for the old
block seven and sort of pretend that
block e refers to it and now block this
new block seven doesn't have a
transaction and so that sort of very
straightforward changing of a single
block doesn't work and the reason is
that these arrows here are really really
means that there's a cryptographic hash
and blog ate that
is the hash of the block seven it refers
to and so this hashing blockade you know
for for a block seven that already
exists this hashman block eight is a
hash of the original block seven if
someone changes this content it's gonna
have a different hash and so this
blockade hash if you try to pawn off
this modified block on somebody who
knows about block eight they're gonna
say we didn't have our keys you know
hash doesn't hash to the same no block
this block seven prime doesn't hash to
the same value that's embedded in Block
E so you can't trick anybody who knows
about subsequent blocks into accepting a
modified intermediate block alright
question
I see why is a Q store by his coffee it
shows up in one of the blocks
oh I see ok so this is a let me just
back up a little bit so I think the
scenario we have is that you know there
was a blockchain and then a brief fork
and in that brief fork why pay the same
coin to two different two different
parties and let's say this is block 7
prime prime and it's block 7 that wins
and is on the main chain and block 7
prime prime is it's just forgotten and
ignored and the question is jeez you
know for briefly at least Q saw this
transaction show up in the chain and
gave the cup of coffee to why and then
why I left the store but then you know
this part of the chain is discarded and
Q is left with no money they've given
away some coffee but they did not get
paid and that just is what happens in
this scenario all right if Q was willing
to handle with a cup of coffee after
seeing the transaction in just the last
block in the blockchain then they'd risk
this scenario and there's nothing they
can do about it and they can't get the
money back I mean unless you run down
the street catch up with the person and
take the cup of coffee away and that is
the reason why for high-value
transactions your Starbucks trolley
doesn't care very much right that cup of
coffee really only cost like you know 50
cents to make like if they occasionally
you know these Forks don't happen that
often they occasionally lose a cup of
coffee well they can probably willing to
deal with that but if if why was buying
a car from Q for you know $20,000
Bitcoin thank you probably would rather
not let Y walk off with this level of
assurance that being paid and that's the
reason why if you care you'll wait until
multiple blocks show up after the block
in which in which your transaction was
in so Z won't actually him if it's a
high-value transactions he won't hand
over the goods until there's at least
some number five six blocks showing up
after the block
Action Shooting open and it's very
unlikely that a a fork could be extended
at five or six times like over a period
of an hour now ken block's show up only
every ten minutes and then turn out to
be the shortest not the longest chain
because that means that there was some
other fork that was extending faster and
the only way some other before could
extend faster is that if a majority of
the cpu power was working on it and
we're assuming that a majority the cpu
power is islam malicious and is
therefore switching to the current
longest chain all right so this is you
have to be if you're doing large value
transactions you have to be careful and
wait till a chain goes long and after
your transaction shows up okay so okay
so I explained why you can't simply
modify a block in the middle of the
chain there's a related question which
is supposing there's an existing
blockchain you know that's something
that long and your transaction Y arrow
transaction why does he shows up here in
the blockchain and you want to get rid
you want to hide that transaction now
somehow make it so it doesn't exist well
gosh why don't you produce a new sort of
alternate chain that you know is mostly
identical to the main the real chain but
it's longer and just happens to omit Y
is transferred to Z and instead includes
Y is transferred to Q and if you do the
mining correctly for this and the hashes
work out your chains longer and it just
will be accepted under the rules of
Bitcoin which which everybody supposed
to switch to the longest chain so how
come you can't do this
and this you know this would also allow
you to double spend by essentially
unspent in a previous spent quantity and
my earlier comment about oh you're
supposed to wait you know zis was to
wait until the blockchain gets extended
you know this is now a way to defeat Z
waiting for the blockchain to extend it
so we're really because serious trouble
if you could make this work okay so and
somewhat well the answer is yes this can
be made to work and here's how to do it
you know the main blockchain is being
extended by the non malicious
participants at some rate right they
have enough CPU power to you know
produce a new block every 10 minutes if
you're the attacker and you have more
CPU power than the entire non-malicious
set appears then you're going to be able
to generate walks faster than the real
chain so your block makes your you know
chain may start out shorter and I may
take you a while to generate each block
but you know maybe you can generate two
blocks every ten minutes whereas the
main chain is only capable of generating
one block every ten minutes so that
means that for a while you'll have
caught up and exceeded the length of the
main chain the main fork and by the
rules of Bitcoin everyone you
non-malicious totally correct Bitcoin
peers they'll all switch to your longer
chain and that means they'll all
effectively forget this transaction and
except this other transaction this
second spend of the same coin so if
you're an attacker and you have more CPU
power than the entire rest of the
network
you can produce this chain and it means
you can double spend and you know that's
certainly you know something to think
about but the reason why you might hope
more be sort of somewhat confident that
it couldn't arise is that in a big
system with lots of participants it
might be very hard to assemble more CPU
power than the entire rest of the system
so once the buns Bitcoin grew big you
know people were somewhat confident that
the main sort of non-malicious system
had enough cpu power that it would be
expensive for an attacker to assemble
more CPU power than the rest of the
system of course for new
cryptocurrencies that don't yet have
very large mining operations going
they're actually easy to shoot down it's
easy for a new cryptocurrency like
Bitcoin it's easy for an attacker you
know for whatever reason to put it out
of business by getting more CPU power
but for a big system like Bitcoin it's
somewhat difficult now that said the
people who've looked into tried to
figure out who controls mining CPU power
and Bitcoin suspect that the biggest
players have fractions of the total that
are not that far from 50% and that
certainly if you know two or three of
the largest mining operations combined
forces that they would have a majority
of the mining power in Bitcoin and could
produce alternate Forks like this so
that's a somewhat troubling development
you know whether there'd be motivated to
do something bad especially since sort
of everything that's done in Bitcoin is
public that's what people would really
notice that oh gosh that was a long
chain and then we switch to a chain that
started way far back boy would people
ever notice that and that would you know
destroy confidence in Bitcoin and may
undermine anything that the malicious
parties were hoping to achieve
so since you know it is very expensive
actually you know the big players in
mining in Bitcoin I spent a huge amount
of money to buy the mining hardware that
they owned and so they probably wouldn't
want to undermine people's trust in
Bitcoin because that would destroy the
value of their vast collections partner
all right any questions about the
machinery here all right so I
questions that I can ask an answer one
question is that the ten minutes between
blocks is actually a serious annoyance
it means that if I want to buy something
it takes up to 10 minutes before the
transaction shows up in the blockchain
at all
even even in the first block and you
know either I have to wait around for 10
minutes to get my cup of coffee or the
store owner has to give me my cup of
coffee before the trans before the
transactions in the blockchain at all
thus having to trust me so why can't we
make the 10 minutes much shorter and you
know actually the 10 minutes probably
could be made shorter the practical
reasons why it isn't shorter is that it
actually it takes a while for new box to
be flooded over the system right after a
miner finds the next block it has to be
sent thousands of peers Bitcoin over
possibly slow network connections and it
may take quite a while before that block
is known to all the other peers and that
means that there's some period of time
in which other peers are mining on
blocks or wasting their time mining
blocks that are I've been superseded by
a block that hasn't yet beached them and
basically the fraction of time you spend
mining wasting of trying mining blocks
that have been superseded is related to
how long it takes to mine each block
compared to how long it takes to flood
the block and so if you make the inter
block interval shorter and shorter then
it starts to it gets small enough that
it approaches the amount of time it
takes the flood new blocks and that
would cause most piers to waste most of
their mining effort and since the miners
are actually making money making Bitcoin
by mining because there's a little
reward to the successful miner of each
block the miners are very uninterested
in wasting resources mining for blocks
that are have been superseded and so
they're very uninterested in
this 10-minutes be much shorter than it
it's now and you know that's a
significant constraint so there's a
question what prevents why from double
spending much in a much later block when
piers might have forgotten about the
first transaction and so you know the
question is oh you know in a very early
block why transferred according to Z and
then there are thousand blocks later Y
tries to transfer the same coin to Q you
know like a year later or something and
the answer to how this plays out is that
all the peers remember this forever
they absolutely remember every unspent
transaction forever and that means that
actually that can't be the first
I think nominally to tell you the truth
I don't understand all the ins and outs
of this but one way the most
straightforward way to solve this
problem is for all peers to remember
every transaction forever and every
incoming transaction they check to make
sure that the coin hasn't been spent yet
they just the course create a database
or index or something but allows them to
essentially check every record to see if
this coin has already been spent and I
think you can although I don't fully
understand this I think peers can
discard a lot of though a lot of this
information by only remembering
information about unspent transactions
so they keep a database of unspent
transactions but it doesn't include
spent coins and if a new transactions
coin isn't in the database of unspent
transactions then it's just ignored but
this you know this database has to be
every pair has to keep this database
forever so you know just of course this
is a in a way a very expensive system
because what we're talking about is you
know maintaining a record of every
transaction essentially forever and you
know if you think about how many
transactions there are per second or per
year on earth
it's a vast number and so people really
were serious about using Bitcoin they
used it for everything in the way they
use cash now it would you know it would
be an enormous system and there would be
enormous performance streams on the
system and indeed Bitcoin is not really
capable of supporting every transaction
you couldn't run the entire financial
system of the world on Bitcoin as it
exists today and there's a bunch of
there's a bunch of limits you know one
limit is that the full Bitcoin database
already consumes a couple hundred
gigabytes yeah that's actually not so
bad because you can fit it on a disk but
if it was a thousand times larger it
would start to be a serious problem to
even store it let alone search for stuff
in it the most immediate problem
and we it turns out that processing that
transactions it's not terribly expensive
because for the peers it's mostly about
hashing and these cryptographic hashes
are pretty quick but the sort of most
current you know ugly restriction is
that these block cuz there's a limit to
how big these blocks can be these blocks
can only be a couple megabytes in size
and new blocks appear only every ten
minutes and so that means you only get
you know less than a megabyte of new
transactions per minute each transaction
the sort of Val you know is very way
various ways of abbreviating them but
you know each transaction is at least
dozens or a hundred bytes and that means
that the system can really only because
of this block size limit and the ten
minute limit the system can only process
sort of thousands or tens of thousands
of transactions well I'm not sure I can
divide properly but it's not nearly
enough to run the current way that
Bitcoin set up is not nearly
high-capacity enough to run the world
all the world's financial transactions
are and so you know people change it it
evolves but it's not really fast enough
for everything of course nobody's really
using it for commerce it's mostly used
for speculation as far as anyone can
tell so it's not yet a problem but from
a design point that there needs to be
some things fixed okay so I mentioned
before that the Bitcoin software adjusts
the hardness of finding nonces that is
the number of required leading zeros in
the block hash adjusts that dynamically
to cause there to be ten minutes for
block one thing that has to be the case
though is that all the participants have
to agree on the required number of
leading zeros they actually all have to
agree on the hardness of finding a knots
and so if one peer sort of looks at the
rate at which blocks have been produced
and
besides that it's too slow and it should
make the require fewer leading zeros but
the other peers haven't made the same
decision then that first piers will be
generating blocks that are rejected by
the other peers because all the peers
demand what they think is the correct
number of leading zeros in the hash so
there has to be agreement on on the
hardness of finding a nots
that the the peers have to agree exactly
and what the current hardness is
otherwise they'll reject each other's
blocks so how do they reach that
agreement it turns out actually to be
totally straightforward they all are
looking at the same blockchain after all
that was the whole point is that you
know except for temporary Forks there's
just one blockchain everybody hasn't a
copy of the exact same bits in the
blockchain and so the Bitcoin just
defines a deterministic function that
takes the current blockchain as its
argument and uses that to
deterministically produce the current
hardness of finding a nonce and the way
it does that is basically it looks at
the timestamps in the blocks to decide
how fast the recent blocks have been
produced but since everybody's looking
at the same blocks in the same time
stamps and is running the same function
to adjust the hardness they all come to
exactly the same conclusion about what
the hardness ought to be for for each
successive block in the blockchain so
there's a kind of interesting agreement
that's being enforced there because they
all see the identical same laws all
right
another interesting question is that one
of the motivations that some people have
for being interested in new
cryptocurrencies is that they might be
more anonymous than credit cards and
indeed credit cards are deeply
non-anonymous since the credit card
company knows exactly what you're up to
I keeps a record of it whereas Bitcoin
at least on the face of it you know
Bitcoin there was nothing about a
Bitcoin transaction that say had my name
on it
now you might think well each Bitcoin
transaction has my public key in it
man that's true if I don't change my
public key and I always use the same
public key then once somebody figures
out my public key is just relatively
easy since whenever I pay somebody they
they get to know my public key then
people can track my activities by
looking for my public key or my
signature in the Bitcoin lock and it's a
public log so anybody can look now
people everybody who cares and I think
most Bitcoin wallets offer actually
generates fresh public keys for each
transaction I'm said anytime if somebody
wants to pay me money my wallet will
generate a new never used before public
private key pair
remember the private key then give the
public key to the person who wants to
send me money and that makes the
tracking harder but it turns out that if
you're up against determined sleuth
there's you know there's enough clues if
you make transactions often enough since
the transactions are often tied to your
real identity like if you buy something
from Amazon with Bitcoin yeah maybe the
Bitcoin transaction it's not clear it's
you but it probably needs to be shipped
to you by FedEx to your home address and
that's a little piece of identifying
information there and that will allow
somebody to figure out it was you who
spent that money and they'll be able to
straight track backwards to see where
that money came from to get another clue
about who you are and what you're up to
so in fact against amateurs Bitcoin is
reasonably anonymous against serious
adversaries a Bitcoin has turned out not
to be particularly anonymous okay
a little bit disappointing from a little
bit disappointing for people who are
interested in privacy or doing drug
deals or financing illegal activity
alright
sum up the sort of key idea here is the
blockchain like a public ledger that
everybody agrees on and that has every
transaction on it and all that has a lot
of problems like with scalability if you
can make it work it's a great idea
another sort of key technical problem is
how to do this without any
centralization now whether the
centralization or decentralization of
valuable property is kind of not really
a technical question but if you value it
then it's just really cool and amazing
but it's possible to have agreement on a
single log with no central trust and I'm
using participants many of whom are
actively malicious and the final key
idea is that is the idea of mining a
proof-of-work where it too has problems
but it's very surprising that a
technique existed at all that allowed
agreement in a way that can't be fooled
by these sort of fake IP address attacks
that doesn't suffer the same problems
that voting suffers that was a very
surprising and interesting development
all right that's all I have to say the
actually sent kind of continuing some of
this line of thought and the next
lecture which is a sort of different
kind of decentralized system partially
built on top of Bitcoin